<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!--<!DOCTYPE appendix PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.3//EN"
                      "http://www.docbook.org/xml/4.3/docbookx.dtd" [
<!ENTITY % globalents SYSTEM "../global.ent">
%globalents;
]>-->
<appendix id="LPI_certification">
    <title>Linux Professional Institute (LPI) Certification</title>
    <sect1>
        <title>Introduction</title>
        <para>Visit <ulink url="http://www.lpi.org/en/lpic.html">this site</ulink>for the latest
            information. The following section will describe the certification methods and
            pre-requisite knowledge that is needed to gain the LPI certifications.</para>
        <sect2>
            <title>Junior Level Administration (LPIC1)</title>
            <para>Status: Available since January 2000, latest revision done in March 2003
                Pre-requisite Knowledge: none Requirements: Pass exam 101 and 102 Job description of
                a person with this certification:</para>
            <itemizedlist>
                <listitem>
                    <para>Work at the Linux command line</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>Perform easy maintenance tasks: help out users, add users to a larger
                        system, backup &#38; restore, shutdown &#38; reboot</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>Install and configure a workstation (including X) and connect it to a LAN,
                        or a stand-alone PC via modem to the Internet.</para>
                </listitem>
            </itemizedlist>
            <sect3>
                <title>LPI exam 101 Details</title>
                <bridgehead>Topic 101 Hardware and Architecture</bridgehead>
                <table pgwide="0">
                    <title>LPI exam 101: Hardware and Architecture</title>
                    <tgroup align="left" cols="4" colsep="1" rowsep="1">
                        <colspec colname="Weight" colwidth="0.5*"/>
                        <colspec colname="Title" colwidth="1.7*"/>
                        <colspec colname="Description" colwidth="4*"/>
                        <colspec colname="Key Files, terms and utillities" colwidth="2.5*"/>
                        <tbody>
                            <row>
                                <entry>Weight</entry>
                                <entry>Title</entry>
                                <entry>Description</entry>
                                <entry>Key Files, terms and utillities</entry>
                            </row>
                            <row>
                                <entry>1</entry>
                                <entry>Fundamental BIOS Settings</entry>
                                <entry>Candidates should be able to configure fundamental system
                                    hardware by making the correct settings in the system BIOS. This
                                    objective includes a proper understanding of BIOS configuration
                                    issues such as the use of LBA on IDE hard disks larger than 1024
                                    cylinders, enabling or disabling integrated peripherals, as well
                                    as configuring systems with (or without) external peripherals
                                    such as keyboards. It also includes the correct setting for IRQ,
                                    DMA and I/O addresses for all BIOS administrated ports and
                                    settings for error handling.</entry>
                                <entry>/proc/ioports /proc/interrupts /proc/dma /proc/pci</entry>
                            </row>
                            <row>
                                <entry>1</entry>
                                <entry>Configure Modem and Sound cards</entry>
                                <entry>Ensure devices meet compatibility requirements (particularly
                                    that the modem is NOT a win-modem), verify that both the modem
                                    and sound card are using unique and correct IRQ's, I/O, and DMA
                                    addresses, if the sound card is PnP install and run sndconfig
                                    and isapnp, configure modem for outbound dial-up, configure
                                    modem for outbound PPP | SLIP | CSLIP connection, set serial
                                    port for 115.2 Kbps</entry>
                                <entry>Not applicable</entry>
                            </row>
                            <row>
                                <entry>1</entry>
                                <entry>Setup SCSI Devices</entry>
                                <entry>Candidates should be able to configure SCSI devices using the
                                    SCSI BIOS as well as the necessary Linux tools. They also should
                                    be able to differentiate between the various types of SCSI. This
                                    objective includes manipulating the SCSI BIOS to detect used and
                                    available SCSI IDs and setting the correct ID number for
                                    different devices especially the boot device. It also includes
                                    managing the settings in the computer's BIOS to determine the
                                    desired boot sequence if both SCSI and IDE drives are used.</entry>
                                <entry>SCSI ID /proc/scsi/ scsi_info</entry>
                            </row>
                            <row>
                                <entry>1</entry>
                                <entry>Configure Communication Devices</entry>
                                <entry>Candidates should be able to install and configure different
                                    internal and external communication devices like modems, ISDN
                                    adapters, and DSL switches. This objective includes verification
                                    of compatibility requirements (especially important if that
                                    modem is a winmodem), necessary hardware settings for internal
                                    devices (IRQs, DMAs, I/O ports), and loading and configuring
                                    suitable device drivers. It also includes communication device
                                    and interface configuration requirements, such as the right
                                    serial port for 115.2 Kbps, and the correct modem settings for
                                    outbound PPP connection(s).</entry>
                                <entry>/proc/dma /proc/interrupts /proc/ioports setserial(8)</entry>
                            </row>
                            <row>
                                <entry>1</entry>
                                <entry>Configure USB devices</entry>
                                <entry>Candidates should be able to activate USB support, use and
                                    configure different USB devices. This objective includes the
                                    correct selection of the USB chipset and the corresponding
                                    module. It also includes the knowledge of the basic architecture
                                    of the layer model of USB as well as the different modules used
                                    in the different layers. Key files, terms, and utilities include:</entry>
                                <entry>lspci(8) usb-uhci.o usb-ohci.o /etc/usbmgr/ usbmodules /etc/hotplug</entry>
                            </row>
                            <row>
                                <entry>3</entry>
                                <entry>Setup different PC expansion cards</entry>
                                <entry>Candidates should be able to configure various cards for the
                                    various expansion slots. They should know the differences
                                    between ISA and PCI cards with respect to configuration issues.
                                    This objective includes the correct settings of IRQs, DMAs and
                                    I/O Ports of the cards, especially to avoid conflicts between
                                    devices. It also includes using isapnp if the card is an ISA PnP device.</entry>
                                <entry>/proc/dma /proc/interrupts /proc/ioports /proc/pci pnpdump(8)
                                    isapnp(8) lspci(8)</entry>
                            </row>
                        </tbody>
                    </tgroup>
                </table>
                <bridgehead>Topic 102 Linux Installation &#38; Package Management</bridgehead>
                <table pgwide="0">
                    <title>LPI exam 101: Linux Installation &#38; Package Management</title>
                    <tgroup align="left" cols="4" colsep="1" rowsep="1">
                        <colspec colname="Weight" colwidth="0.5*"/>
                        <colspec colname="Title" colwidth="1.7*"/>
                        <colspec colname="Description" colwidth="4*"/>
                        <colspec colname="Key Files, terms and utillities" colwidth="2.5*"/>
                        <tbody>
                            <row>
                                <entry>Weight</entry>
                                <entry>Title</entry>
                                <entry>Description</entry>
                                <entry>Key Files, terms and utillities</entry>
                            </row>
                            <row>
                                <entry>1</entry>
                                <entry>Install a boot manager</entry>
                                <entry>Candidate should be able to select, install, and configure a
                                    boot manager. This objective includes providing alternative boot
                                    locations and backup boot options (for example, using a boot floppy).</entry>
                                <entry>/etc/lilo.conf /boot/grub/grub.conf lilo grub-install MBR
                                    superblock first stage boot loader</entry>
                            </row>
                            <row>
                                <entry>3</entry>
                                <entry>Manage shared libraries</entry>
                                <entry>Candidates should be able to determine the shared libraries
                                    that executable programs depend on and install them when
                                    necessary. Candidates should be able to state where system
                                    libraries are kept.</entry>
                                <entry>ldd ldconfig /etc/ld.so.conf LD_LIBRARY_PATH</entry>
                            </row>
                            <row>
                                <entry>5</entry>
                                <entry>Design hard disk layout</entry>
                                <entry>Candidates should be able to design a disk partitioning
                                    scheme for a Linux system. This objective includes allocating
                                    filesystems or swap space to separate partitions or disks, and
                                    tailoring the design to the intended use of the system. It also
                                    includes placing /boot on a partition that conforms with the
                                    BIOS' requirements for booting.</entry>
                                <entry>/ (root) filesystem /var filesystem /home filesystem swap
                                    space mount points partitions cylinder 1024</entry>
                            </row>
                            <row>
                                <entry>5</entry>
                                <entry>Make and install programs from source</entry>
                                <entry>Candidates should be able to build and install an executable
                                    program from source. This objective includes being able to
                                    unpack a file of sources. Candidates should be able to make
                                    simple customizations to the Makefile, for example changing
                                    paths or adding extra include directories.</entry>
                                <entry>gunzip gzip bzip2 tar configure make</entry>
                            </row>
                            <row>
                                <entry>8</entry>
                                <entry>Use Debian package management</entry>
                                <entry>Candidates should be able to perform package management
                                    skills using the Debian package manager. This objective includes
                                    being able to use command-line and interactive tools to install,
                                    upgrade, or uninstall packages, as well as find packages
                                    containing specific files or software (such packages might or
                                    might not be installed). This objective also includes being able
                                    to obtain package information like version, content,
                                    dependencies, package integrity and installation status (whether
                                    or not the package is installed).</entry>
                                <entry>unpack configure /etc/dpkg/dpkg.cfg /var/lib/dpkg/*
                                    /etc/apt/apt.conf /etc/apt/sources.list dpkg dselect
                                    dpkg-reconfigure apt-get alien</entry>
                            </row>
                            <row>
                                <entry>8</entry>
                                <entry>Use Red Hat Package Manager (RPM)</entry>
                                <entry>Candidates should be able to perform package management under
                                    Linux distributions that use RPMs for package distribution. This
                                    objective includes being able to install, re-install, upgrade,
                                    and remove packages, as well as obtain status and version
                                    information on packages. This objective also includes obtaining
                                    package information such as version, status, dependencies,
                                    integrity, and signatures. Candidates should be able to
                                    determine what files a package provides, as well as find which
                                    package a specific file comes from.</entry>
                                <entry>/etc/rpmrc /usr/lib/rpm/* rpm grep</entry>
                            </row>
                        </tbody>
                    </tgroup>
                </table>
                <bridgehead>Topic 103: GNU &#38; Unix Commands</bridgehead>
                <table pgwide="0">
                    <title>LPI exam 101: GNU &#38; Unix Commands</title>
                    <tgroup align="left" cols="4" colsep="1" rowsep="1">
                        <colspec colname="Weight" colwidth="0.5*"/>
                        <colspec colname="Title" colwidth="1.7*"/>
                        <colspec colname="Description" colwidth="4*"/>
                        <colspec colname="Key Files, terms and utillities" colwidth="2.5*"/>
                        <tbody>
                            <row>
                                <entry>Weight</entry>
                                <entry>Title</entry>
                                <entry>Description</entry>
                                <entry>Key Files, terms and utillities</entry>
                            </row>
                            <row>
                                <entry>1</entry>
                                <entry>Perform basic file editing operations using vi</entry>
                                <entry>Candidates should be able to edit text files using vi. This
                                    objective includes vi navigation, basic vi nodes, inserting,
                                    editing, deleting, copying, and finding text.</entry>
                                <entry>vi /, ? h,j,k,l G, H, L i, c, d, dd, p, o, a ZZ, :w!, :q!,
                                    :e! :!</entry>
                            </row>
                            <row>
                                <entry>3</entry>
                                <entry>Modify process execution priorities</entry>
                                <entry>Candidates should should be able to manage process execution
                                    priorities. Tasks include running a program with higher or lower
                                    priority, determining the priority of a process and changing the
                                    priority of a running process.</entry>
                                <entry>nice ps renice top</entry>
                            </row>
                            <row>
                                <entry>3</entry>
                                <entry>Perform basic file management</entry>
                                <entry>Candidates should be able to use the basic Unix commands to
                                    copy, move, and remove files and directories. Tasks include
                                    advanced file management operations such as copying multiple
                                    files recursively, removing directories recursively, and moving
                                    files that meet a wildcard pattern. This includes using simple
                                    and advanced wildcard specifications to refer to files, as well
                                    as using find to locate and act on files based on type, size, or time.</entry>
                                <entry>cp find mkdir mv ls rm rmdir touch file globbing</entry>
                            </row>
                            <row>
                                <entry>3</entry>
                                <entry>Search text files using regular expressions</entry>
                                <entry>Candidates should be able to manipulate files and text data
                                    using regular expressions. This objective includes creating
                                    simple regular expressions containing several notational
                                    elements. It also includes using regular expression tools to
                                    perform searches through a filesystem or file content.</entry>
                                <entry>grep regexp sed</entry>
                            </row>
                            <row>
                                <entry>5</entry>
                                <entry>Work on the command line</entry>
                                <entry>Candidates should be able to Interact with shells and
                                    commands using the command line. This includes typing valid
                                    commands and command sequences, defining, referencing and
                                    exporting environment variables, using command history and
                                    editing facilities, invoking commands in the path and outside
                                    the path, using command substitution, applying commands
                                    recursively through a directory tree and using man to find out
                                    about commands.</entry>
                                <entry>. bash echo env exec export man pwd set unset ~/.bash_history ~/.profile</entry>
                            </row>
                            <row>
                                <entry>5</entry>
                                <entry>Use streams, pipes, and redirects</entry>
                                <entry>Candidates should be able to redirect streams and connect
                                    them in order to efficiently process textual data. Tasks include
                                    redirecting standard input, standard output, and standard error,
                                    piping the output of one command to the input of another
                                    command, using the output of one command as arguments to another
                                    command and sending output to both stdout and a file.</entry>
                                <entry>tee xargs &lt; &lt;&lt; &gt;&gt; | ' '</entry>
                            </row>
                            <row>
                                <entry>5</entry>
                                <entry>Create, monitor, and kill processes</entry>
                                <entry>Candidates should be able to manage processes. This includes
                                    knowing how to run jobs in the foreground and background, bring
                                    a job from the background to the foreground and vice versa,
                                    start a process that will run without being connected to a
                                    terminal and signal a program to continue running after logout.
                                    Tasks also include monitoring active processes, selecting and
                                    sorting processes for display, sending signals to processes,
                                    killing processes and identifying and killing X applications
                                    that did not terminate after the X session closed.</entry>
                                <entry>&#38; bg fg jobs kill nohup ps top</entry>
                            </row>
                            <row>
                                <entry>6</entry>
                                <entry>Process text streams using filters</entry>
                                <entry>Candidates should should be able to apply filters to text
                                    streams. Tasks include sending text files and output streams
                                    through text utility filters to modify the output, and using
                                    standard Unix commands found in the GNU textutils package.</entry>
                                <entry>cat cut expand fmt head join nl od paste pr sed sort split
                                    tac tail tr unexpand uniq wc</entry>
                            </row>
                        </tbody>
                    </tgroup>
                </table>
                <bridgehead>Topic 104: Devices, Linux Filesystems, Filesystem Hierarchy Standard</bridgehead>
                <table pgwide="0">
                    <title>LPI exam 101: Devices, Linux Filesystems, Filesystem Hierarchy Standard</title>
                    <tgroup align="left" cols="4" colsep="1" rowsep="1">
                        <colspec colname="Weight" colwidth="0.5*"/>
                        <colspec colname="Title" colwidth="1.7*"/>
                        <colspec colname="Description" colwidth="4*"/>
                        <colspec colname="Key Files, terms and utillities" colwidth="2.5*"/>
                        <tbody>
                            <row>
                                <entry>Weight</entry>
                                <entry>Title</entry>
                                <entry>Description</entry>
                                <entry>Key Files, terms and utillities</entry>
                            </row>
                            <row>
                                <entry>1</entry>
                                <entry>Create and change hard and symbolic links</entry>
                                <entry>Candidates should be able to create and manage hard and
                                    symbolic links to a file. This objective includes the ability to
                                    create and identify links, copy files through links, and use
                                    linked files to support system administration tasks.</entry>
                                <entry>ln</entry>
                            </row>
                            <row>
                                <entry>1</entry>
                                <entry>Manage file ownership</entry>
                                <entry>Candidates should be able to control user and group ownership
                                    of files. This objective includes the ability to change the user
                                    and group owner of a file as well as the default group owner for
                                    new files. Key files, terms, and utilities include:</entry>
                                <entry>chmod chown chgrp</entry>
                            </row>
                            <row>
                                <entry>3</entry>
                                <entry>Create partitions and filesystems</entry>
                                <entry>Candidates should be able to configure disk partitions and
                                    then create filesystems on media such as hard disks. This
                                    objective includes using various mkfs commands to set up
                                    partitions to various filesystems, including ext2, ext3,
                                    reiserfs, vfat, and xfs.</entry>
                                <entry>fdisk mkfs</entry>
                            </row>
                            <row>
                                <entry>3</entry>
                                <entry>Maintain the integrity of filesystems</entry>
                                <entry>Candidates should be able to verify the integrity of
                                    filesystems, monitor free space and inodes, and repair simple
                                    filesystem problems. This objective includes the commands
                                    required to maintain a standard filesystem, as well as the extra
                                    data associated with a journaling filesystem.</entry>
                                <entry>du df fsck e2fsck mke2fs debugfs dumpe2fs tune2fs</entry>
                            </row>
                            <row>
                                <entry>2</entry>
                                <entry>Control mounting and unmounting filesystems</entry>
                                <entry>Candidates should be able to configure the mounting of a
                                    filesystem. This objective includes the ability to manually
                                    mount and unmount filesystems, configure filesystem mounting on
                                    bootup, and configure user mountable removeable filesystems such
                                    as tape drives, floppies, and CDs.</entry>
                                <entry>/etc/fstab mount umount</entry>
                            </row>
                            <row>
                                <entry>3</entry>
                                <entry>Managing disk quota</entry>
                                <entry>Candidates should be able to manage disk quotas for users.
                                    This objective includes setting up a disk quota for a
                                    filesystem, editing, checking, and generating user quota
                                    reports. quotaon</entry>
                                <entry>quota edquota repquota</entry>
                            </row>
                            <row>
                                <entry>5</entry>
                                <entry>Use file permissions to control access to files</entry>
                                <entry>Candidates should be able to control file access through
                                    permissions. This objective includes access permissions on
                                    regular and special files as well as directories. Also included
                                    are access modes such as suid, sgid, and the sticky bit, the use
                                    of the group field to grant file access to workgroups, the
                                    immutable flag, and the default file creation mode.</entry>
                                <entry>chmod umask chattr</entry>
                            </row>
                            <row>
                                <entry>5</entry>
                                <entry>Find system files and place files in the correct location</entry>
                                <entry>Candidates should be thouroughly familiar with the Filesystem
                                    Hierarchy Standard, including typical file locations and
                                    directory classifications. This objective includes the ability
                                    to find files and commands on a Linux system.</entry>
                                <entry>find locate slocate updatedb whereis which /etc/updatedb.conf</entry>
                            </row>
                        </tbody>
                    </tgroup>
                </table>
                <bridgehead>Topic 110: The X Window System</bridgehead>
                <table pgwide="0">
                    <title>LPI exam 101: The X Window System</title>
                    <tgroup align="left" cols="4" colsep="1" rowsep="1">
                        <colspec colname="Weight" colwidth="0.5*"/>
                        <colspec colname="Title" colwidth="1.7*"/>
                        <colspec colname="Description" colwidth="4*"/>
                        <colspec colname="Key Files, terms and utillities" colwidth="2.5*"/>
                        <tbody>
                            <row>
                                <entry>Weight</entry>
                                <entry>Title</entry>
                                <entry>Description</entry>
                                <entry>Key Files, terms and utillities</entry>
                            </row>
                            <row>
                                <entry>3</entry>
                                <entry>Setup a display manager</entry>
                                <entry>Candidate should be able setup and customize a Display
                                    manager. This objective includes turning the display manager on
                                    or off and changing the display manager greeting. This objective
                                    includes changing default bitplanes for the display manager. It
                                    also includes configuring display managers for use by
                                    X-stations. This objective covers the display managers XDM (X
                                    Display Manger), GDM (Gnome Display Manager) and KDM (KDE
                                    Display Manager).</entry>
                                <entry>/etc/inittab /etc/X11/xdm/* /etc/X11/kdm/* /etc/X11/gdm/*</entry>
                            </row>
                            <row>
                                <entry>5</entry>
                                <entry>Install &#38; Configure XFree86</entry>
                                <entry>Candidate should be able to configure and install X and an X
                                    font server. This objective includes verifying that the video
                                    card and monitor are supported by an X server, as well as
                                    customizing and tuning X for the videocard and monitor. It also
                                    includes installing an X font server, installing fonts, and
                                    configuring X to use the font server (may require a manual edit
                                    of /etc/X11/XF86Config in the &quot;Files&quot; section).</entry>
                                <entry>XF86Setup xf86config xvidtune /etc/X11/XF86Config .Xresources</entry>
                            </row>
                            <row>
                                <entry>5</entry>
                                <entry>Install &#38; Customize a Window Manager Environment</entry>
                                <entry>Candidate should be able to customize a system-wide desktop
                                    environment and/or window manager, to demonstrate an
                                    understanding of customization procedures for window manager
                                    menus and/or desktop panel menus. This objective includes
                                    selecting and configuring the desired x-terminal (xterm, rxvt,
                                    aterm etc.), verifying and resolving library dependency issues
                                    for X applications, exporting X-display to a client workstation</entry>
                                <entry>.xinitrc .Xdefaults xhost DISPLAY environment variable</entry>
                            </row>
                        </tbody>
                    </tgroup>
                </table>
            </sect3>
            <sect3>
                <title>LPI Exam 102</title>
                <bridgehead>Topic 105: Kernel</bridgehead>
                <table pgwide="0">
                    <title>LPI Exam 102: The kernel</title>
                    <tgroup align="left" cols="4" colsep="1" rowsep="1">
                        <colspec colname="Weight" colwidth="0.5*"/>
                        <colspec colname="Title" colwidth="1.7*"/>
                        <colspec colname="Description" colwidth="4*"/>
                        <colspec colname="Key Files, terms and utillities" colwidth="2.5*"/>
                        <tbody>
                            <row>
                                <entry>Weight</entry>
                                <entry>Title</entry>
                                <entry>Description</entry>
                                <entry>Key Files, terms and utillities</entry>
                            </row>
                            <row>
                                <entry>3</entry>
                                <entry>Reconfigure, build, and install a custom kernel and kernel modules</entry>
                                <entry>Candidates should be able to customize, build, and install a
                                    kernel and kernel loadable modules from source This objective
                                    includes customizing the current kernel configuration, building
                                    a new kernel, and building kernel modules as appropriate. It
                                    also includes installing the new kernel as well as any modules,
                                    and ensuring that the boot manager can locate the new kernel and
                                    associated files (generally located under /boot, see objective
                                    1.102.2 for more details about boot manager configuration).</entry>
                                <entry>/usr/src/Linux/* /usr/src/Linux/.config
                                    /lib/modules/kernel-version/* /boot/* make make targets: config,
                                    menuconfig, xconfig, oldconfig, modules, install,
                                    modules_install, depmod</entry>
                            </row>
                            <row>
                                <entry/>
                                <entry/>
                                <entry/>
                                <entry/>
                            </row>
                            <row>
                                <entry>4</entry>
                                <entry>Manage/Query kernel and kernel modules at runtime</entry>
                                <entry>Candidates should be able to manage and/or query a kernel and
                                    kernel loadable modules. This objective includes using
                                    command-line utilities to get information about the currently
                                    running kernel and kernel modules. It also includes manually
                                    loading and unloading modules as appropriate. It also includes
                                    being able to determine when modules can be unloaded and what
                                    parameters a module accepts. Candidates should be able to
                                    configure the system to load modules by names other than their
                                    file name.</entry>
                                <entry>/lib/modules/kernel-version/modules.dep /etc/modules.conf
                                    &#38; /etc/conf.modules depmod insmod lsmod rmmod modinfo
                                    modprobe uname</entry>
                            </row>
                        </tbody>
                    </tgroup>
                </table>
                <bridgehead>Topic 106: Boot, Initialization, Shutdown and Runlevels</bridgehead>
                <table pgwide="0">
                    <title>LPI Exam 102: Boot, Initialization, Shutdown and Runlevels</title>
                    <tgroup align="left" cols="4" colsep="1" rowsep="1">
                        <colspec colname="Weight" colwidth="0.5*"/>
                        <colspec colname="Title" colwidth="1.7*"/>
                        <colspec colname="Description" colwidth="4*"/>
                        <colspec colname="Key Files, terms and utillities" colwidth="2.5*"/>
                        <tbody>
                            <row>
                                <entry>Weight</entry>
                                <entry>Title</entry>
                                <entry>Description</entry>
                                <entry>Key Files, terms and utillities</entry>
                            </row>
                            <row>
                                <entry>3</entry>
                                <entry>Boot the system</entry>
                                <entry>Candidates should be able to guide the system through the
                                    booting process. This includes giving commands to the boot
                                    loader and giving options to the kernel at boot time, and
                                    checking the events in the log files.</entry>
                                <entry>/var/log/messages /etc/conf.modules or /etc/modules.conf
                                    dmesg LILO GRUB</entry>
                            </row>
                            <row>
                                <entry>3</entry>
                                <entry>Change runlevels and shutdown or reboot system</entry>
                                <entry>Candidates should be able to manage the runlevel of the
                                    system. This objective includes changing to single user mode,
                                    shutdown or rebooting the system. Candidates should be able to
                                    alert users before switching runlevel, and properly terminate
                                    processes. This objective also includes setting the default runlevel.</entry>
                                <entry>/etc/inittab shutdown init</entry>
                            </row>
                        </tbody>
                    </tgroup>
                </table>
                <bridgehead>Topic 107: Printing</bridgehead>
                <table pgwide="0">
                    <title>LPI Exam 102: Printing</title>
                    <tgroup align="left" cols="4" colsep="1" rowsep="1">
                        <colspec colname="Weight" colwidth="0.5*"/>
                        <colspec colname="Title" colwidth="1.7*"/>
                        <colspec colname="Description" colwidth="4*"/>
                        <colspec colname="Key Files, terms and utillities" colwidth="2.5*"/>
                        <tbody>
                            <row>
                                <entry>Weight</entry>
                                <entry>Title</entry>
                                <entry>Description</entry>
                                <entry>Key Files, terms and utillities</entry>
                            </row>
                            <row>
                                <entry>1</entry>
                                <entry>Manage printers and print queues</entry>
                                <entry>Candidates should be able to manage print queues and user
                                    print jobs. This objective includes monitoring print server and
                                    user print queues and troubleshooting general printing problems.</entry>
                                <entry>/etc/printcap lpc lpq lprm lp</entry>
                            </row>
                            <row>
                                <entry>1</entry>
                                <entry>Print files</entry>
                                <entry>Candidates should be able to manage print queues and
                                    manipulate print jobs. This objective includes adding and
                                    removing jobs from configured printer queues and converting text
                                    files to postscript for printing.</entry>
                                <entry>lpr lpq mpage</entry>
                            </row>
                            <row>
                                <entry>1</entry>
                                <entry>Install and configure local and remote printers</entry>
                                <entry>Candidate should be able to install a printer daemon, install
                                    and configure a print filter (e.g.: apsfilter, magicfilter).
                                    This objective includes making local and remote printers
                                    accessible for a Linux system, including postscript,
                                    non-postscript, and Samba printers.</entry>
                                <entry>/etc/printcap /etc/apsfilter/* /var/lib/apsfilter/*/
                                    /etc/magicfilter/*/ /var/spool/lpd/*/ lpd</entry>
                            </row>
                        </tbody>
                    </tgroup>
                </table>
                <bridgehead>Topic 108: Documentation</bridgehead>
                <table pgwide="0">
                    <title>LPI Exam 102: Documentation</title>
                    <tgroup align="left" cols="4" colsep="1" rowsep="1">
                        <colspec colname="Weight" colwidth="0.5*"/>
                        <colspec colname="Title" colwidth="1.7*"/>
                        <colspec colname="Description" colwidth="4*"/>
                        <colspec colname="Key Files, terms and utillities" colwidth="2.5*"/>
                        <tbody>
                            <row>
                                <entry>Weight</entry>
                                <entry>Title</entry>
                                <entry>Description</entry>
                                <entry>Key Files, terms and utillities</entry>
                            </row>
                            <row>
                                <entry>3</entry>
                                <entry>Find Linux documentation on the Internet</entry>
                                <entry>Candidates should be able to find and use Linux
                                    documentation. This objective includes using Linux documentation
                                    at sources such as the Linux Documentation Project (LDP), vendor
                                    and third-party websites, newsgroups, newsgroup archives, and
                                    mailing lists.</entry>
                                <entry>Not applicable</entry>
                            </row>
                            <row>
                                <entry>4</entry>
                                <entry>Use and manage local system documentation</entry>
                                <entry>Candidates should be able to use and administer the man
                                    facility and the material in /usr/share/doc/. This objective
                                    includes finding relevant man pages, searching man page
                                    sections, finding commands and man pages related to them, and
                                    configuring access to man sources and the man system. It also
                                    includes using system documentation stored in /usr/share/doc/
                                    and determining what documentation to keep in /usr/share/doc/.</entry>
                                <entry>MANPATH man apropos whatis</entry>
                            </row>
                            <row>
                                <entry>1</entry>
                                <entry>Notify users on system-related issues</entry>
                                <entry>Candidates should be able to notify the users about current
                                    issues related to the system. This objective includes automating
                                    the communication process, e.g. through logon messages.</entry>
                                <entry>/etc/issue /etc/issue.net /etc/motd</entry>
                            </row>
                        </tbody>
                    </tgroup>
                </table>
                <bridgehead>Topic 109:</bridgehead>
                <table pgwide="0">
                    <title>LPI Exam 102: Shells, Scripting, Programming and Compiling</title>
                    <tgroup align="left" cols="4" colsep="1" rowsep="1">
                        <colspec colname="Weight" colwidth="0.5*"/>
                        <colspec colname="Title" colwidth="1.7*"/>
                        <colspec colname="Description" colwidth="4*"/>
                        <colspec colname="Key Files, terms and utillities" colwidth="2.5*"/>
                        <tbody>
                            <row>
                                <entry>Weight</entry>
                                <entry>Title</entry>
                                <entry>Description</entry>
                                <entry>Key Files, terms and utillities</entry>
                            </row>
                            <row>
                                <entry/>
                                <entry/>
                                <entry/>
                                <entry/>
                            </row>
                            <row>
                                <entry>3</entry>
                                <entry>Customize or write simple scripts</entry>
                                <entry>Candidate should be able to customize existing scripts, or
                                    write simple new (ba)sh scripts. This objective includes using
                                    standard sh Syntax (loops, tests), using command substitution,
                                    testing command return values, testing of file status, and
                                    conditional mailing to the superuser. This objective also
                                    includes making sure the correct interpreter is called on the
                                    first (#!) line of scripts. This objective also includes
                                    managing location, ownership, execution and suid-rights of scripts.</entry>
                                <entry>while for test chmod</entry>
                            </row>
                            <row>
                                <entry>5</entry>
                                <entry>Customize and use the shell environment</entry>
                                <entry>Candidate should be able to customize shell environments to
                                    meet users' needs. This objective includes setting environment
                                    variables (e.g. PATH) at login or when spawning a new shell. It
                                    also includes writing bash functions for frequently used
                                    sequences of commands.</entry>
                                <entry>~/.bash_profile ~/.bash_login ~/.profile ~/.bashrc
                                    ~/.bash_logout ~/.inputrc function (Bash built-in command)
                                    export env set (Bash built-in command) unset (Bash built-in command)</entry>
                            </row>
                        </tbody>
                    </tgroup>
                </table>
                <bridgehead>Topic 111: Administrative Tasks</bridgehead>
                <table pgwide="0">
                    <title>LPI Exam 102: Administrative Tasks</title>
                    <tgroup align="left" cols="4" colsep="1" rowsep="1">
                        <colspec colname="Weight" colwidth="0.5*"/>
                        <colspec colname="Title" colwidth="1.7*"/>
                        <colspec colname="Description" colwidth="4*"/>
                        <colspec colname="Key Files, terms and utillities" colwidth="2.5*"/>
                        <tbody>
                            <row>
                                <entry>Weight</entry>
                                <entry>Title</entry>
                                <entry>Description</entry>
                                <entry>Key Files, terms and utillities</entry>
                            </row>
                            <row>
                                <entry>3</entry>
                                <entry>Configure and use system log files to meet administrative and
                                    security needs</entry>
                                <entry>Candidate should be able to configure system logs. This
                                    objective includes managing the type and level of information
                                    logged, manually scanning log files for notable activity,
                                    monitoring log files, arranging for automatic rotation and
                                    archiving of logs and tracking down problems noted in logs.</entry>
                                <entry>/etc/syslog.conf /var/log/* logrotate tail -f</entry>
                            </row>
                            <row>
                                <entry>3</entry>
                                <entry>Tune the user environment and system environment variables</entry>
                                <entry>Candidate should be able to modify global and user profiles.
                                    This includes setting environment variables, maintaining skel
                                    directories for new user accounts and setting command search
                                    path with the proper directory.</entry>
                                <entry>/etc/profile /etc/skel env export set unset</entry>
                            </row>
                            <row>
                                <entry>4</entry>
                                <entry>Manage users and group accounts and related system files</entry>
                                <entry>Candidate should be able to add, remove, suspend and change
                                    user accounts. Tasks include to add and remove groups, to change
                                    user/group info in passwd/group databases. The objective also
                                    includes creating special purpose and limited accounts. Key
                                    files, terms, and utilities include:</entry>
                                <entry>/etc/passwd /etc/shadow /etc/group /etc/gshadow chage gpasswd
                                    groupadd groupdel groupmod grpconv grpunconv passwd pwconv
                                    pwunconv useradd userdel usermod</entry>
                            </row>
                            <row>
                                <entry>4</entry>
                                <entry>Automate system administration tasks by scheduling jobs to
                                    run in the future</entry>
                                <entry>Candidate should be able to use cron or anacron to run jobs
                                    at regular intervals and to use at to run jobs at a specific
                                    time. Task include managing cron and at jobs and configuring
                                    user access to cron and at services.</entry>
                                <entry>/etc/anacrontab /etc/at.deny /etc/at.allow /etc/crontab
                                    /etc/cron.allow /etc/cron.deny /var/spool/cron/* at atq atrm crontab</entry>
                            </row>
                            <row>
                                <entry>4</entry>
                                <entry>Maintain an effective data backup strategy</entry>
                                <entry>Candidate should be able to plan a backup strategy and backup
                                    filesystems automatically to various media. Tasks include
                                    dumping a raw device to a file or vice versa, performing partial
                                    and manual backups, verifying the integrity of backup files and
                                    partially or fully restoring backups.</entry>
                                <entry>cpio dd dump restore tar</entry>
                            </row>
                            <row>
                                <entry>4</entry>
                                <entry>Maintain system time</entry>
                                <entry>Candidate should be able to properly maintain the system time
                                    and synchronize the clock over NTP. Tasks include setting the
                                    system date and time, setting the BIOS clock to the correct time
                                    in UTC, configuring the correct timezone for the system and
                                    configuring the system to correct clock drift to match NTP clock.</entry>
                                <entry>/usr/share/zoneinfo /etc/timezone /etc/localtime
                                    /etc/ntp.conf /etc/ntp.drift date hwclock ntpd ntpdate</entry>
                            </row>
                        </tbody>
                    </tgroup>
                </table>
                <bridgehead>Topic 112:</bridgehead>
                <table pgwide="0">
                    <title>LPI Exam 102: Networking Fundamentals</title>
                    <tgroup align="left" cols="4" colsep="1" rowsep="1">
                        <colspec colname="Weight" colwidth="0.5*"/>
                        <colspec colname="Title" colwidth="1.7*"/>
                        <colspec colname="Description" colwidth="4*"/>
                        <colspec colname="Key Files, terms and utillities" colwidth="2.5*"/>
                        <tbody>
                            <row>
                                <entry>Weight</entry>
                                <entry>Title</entry>
                                <entry>Description</entry>
                                <entry>Key Files, terms and utillities</entry>
                            </row>
                            <row>
                                <entry>3</entry>
                                <entry>Configure Linux as a PPP client</entry>
                                <entry>Candidates should understand the basics of the PPP protocol
                                    and be able to configure and use PPP for outbound connections.
                                    This objective includes the definition of the chat sequence to
                                    connect (given a login example) and the setup commands to be run
                                    automatically when a PPP connection is made. It also includes
                                    initialisation and termination of a PPP connection, with a
                                    modem, ISDN or ADSL and setting PPP to automatically reconnect
                                    if disconnected.</entry>
                                <entry>/etc/ppp/options.* /etc/ppp/peers/* /etc/wvdial.conf
                                    /etc/ppp/ip-up /etc/ppp/ip-down wvdial pppd</entry>
                            </row>
                            <row>
                                <entry>4</entry>
                                <entry>Fundamentals of TCP/IP</entry>
                                <entry>Candidates should demonstrate a proper understanding of
                                    network fundamentals. This objective includes the understanding
                                    of IP-addresses, network masks and what they mean (i.e.
                                    determine a network and broadcast address for a host based on
                                    its subnet mask in &quot;dotted quad&quot; or
                                    abbreviated notation or determine the network address, broadcast
                                    address and netmask when given an IP-address and number of
                                    bits). It also covers the understanding of the network classes
                                    and classless subnets (CIDR) and the reserved addresses for
                                    private network use. It includes the understanding of the
                                    function and application of a default route. It also includes
                                    the understanding of basic internet protocols (IP, ICMP, TCP,
                                    UDP) and the more common TCP and UDP ports (20, 21, 23, 25, 53,
                                    80, 110, 119, 139, 143, 161).</entry>
                                <entry>/etc/services ftp telnet host ping dig traceroute whois</entry>
                            </row>
                            <row>
                                <entry>7</entry>
                                <entry>TCP/IP configuration and troubleshooting</entry>
                                <entry>Candidates should be able to view, change and verify
                                    configuration settings and operational status for various
                                    network interfaces. This objective includes manual and automatic
                                    configuration of interfaces and routing tables. This especially
                                    means to add, start, stop, restart, delete or reconfigure
                                    network interfaces. It also means to change, view or configure
                                    the routing table and to correct an improperly set default route
                                    manually. Candidates should be able to configure Linux as a DHCP
                                    client and a TCP/IP host and to debug problems associated with
                                    the network configuration.</entry>
                                <entry>/etc/HOSTNAME or /etc/hostname /etc/hosts /etc/networks
                                    /etc/host.conf /etc/resolv.conf /etc/nsswitch.conf ifconfig
                                    route dhcpcd, dhcpclient, pump host hostname (domainname,
                                    dnsdomainname) netstat ping traceroute tcpdump the network
                                    scripts run during system initialization.</entry>
                            </row>
                        </tbody>
                    </tgroup>
                </table>
                <bridgehead>Topic 113: Networking Services</bridgehead>
                <table pgwide="0">
                    <title>LPI Exam 102: Networking Services</title>
                    <tgroup align="left" cols="4" colsep="1" rowsep="1">
                        <colspec colname="Weight" colwidth="0.5*"/>
                        <colspec colname="Title" colwidth="1.7*"/>
                        <colspec colname="Description" colwidth="4*"/>
                        <colspec colname="Key Files, terms and utillities" colwidth="2.5*"/>
                        <tbody>
                            <row>
                                <entry>Weight</entry>
                                <entry>Title</entry>
                                <entry>Description</entry>
                                <entry>Key Files, terms and utillities</entry>
                            </row>
                            <row>
                                <entry>4</entry>
                                <entry>Setup and configure basic DNS services</entry>
                                <entry>Candidate should be able to configure hostname lookups and
                                    troubleshoot problems with local caching-only name server.
                                    Requires an understanding of the domain registration and DNS
                                    translation process. Requires understanding key differences in
                                    configuration files for bind 4 and bind 8.</entry>
                                <entry>/etc/hosts /etc/resolv.conf /etc/nsswitch.conf
                                    /etc/named.boot (v.4) or /etc/named.conf (v.8) named</entry>
                            </row>
                            <row>
                                <entry>4</entry>
                                <entry>Configure and manage inetd, xinetd, and related services</entry>
                                <entry>Candidates should be able to configure which services are
                                    available through inetd, use tcpwrappers to allow or deny
                                    services on a host-by-host basis, manually start, stop, and
                                    restart internet services, configure basic network services
                                    including telnet and ftp. Set a service to run as another user
                                    instead of the default in inetd.conf.</entry>
                                <entry>/etc/inetd.conf /etc/hosts.allow /etc/hosts.deny
                                    /etc/services /etc/xinetd.conf /etc/xinetd.log</entry>
                            </row>
                            <row>
                                <entry>4</entry>
                                <entry>Operate and perform basic configuration of sendmail</entry>
                                <entry>Candidate should be able to modify simple parameters in
                                    sendmail configuration files (including the &quot;Smart
                                    Host&quot; parameter, if necessary), create mail aliases,
                                    manage the mail queue, start and stop sendmail, configure mail
                                    forwarding and perform basic troubleshooting of sendmail. The
                                    objective includes checking for and closing open relay on the
                                    mailserver. It does not include advanced custom configuration of
                                    Sendmail. Key files, terms, and utilities include:</entry>
                                <entry>/etc/aliases or /etc/mail/aliases /etc/mail/* ~/.forward
                                    mailq sendmail newaliases</entry>
                            </row>
                            <row>
                                <entry>4</entry>
                                <entry>Operate and perform basic configuration of Apache</entry>
                                <entry>Candidates should be able to modify simple parameters in
                                    Apache configuration files, start, stop, and restart httpd,
                                    arrange for automatic restarting of httpd upon boot. Does not
                                    include advanced custom configuration of Apache.</entry>
                                <entry>httpd.conf apachectl httpd</entry>
                            </row>
                            <row>
                                <entry>4</entry>
                                <entry>Properly manage the NFS, smb, and nmb daemons</entry>
                                <entry>Candidate should know how to mount remote filesystems using
                                    NFS, configure NFS for exporting local filesystems, start, stop,
                                    and restart the NFS server. Install and configure Samba using
                                    the included GUI tools or direct edit of the /etc/smb.conf file
                                    (Note: this deliberately excludes advanced NT domain issues but
                                    includes simple sharing of home directories and printers, as
                                    well as correctly setting the nmbd as a WINS client).</entry>
                                <entry>/etc/exports /etc/fstab /etc/smb.conf mount umount</entry>
                            </row>
                            <row>
                                <entry>4</entry>
                                <entry>Set up secure shell (OpenSSH)</entry>
                                <entry>The candidate should be able to obtain and configure OpenSSH.
                                    This objective includes basic OpenSSH installation and
                                    troubleshooting, as well as configuring sshd to start at system boot..</entry>
                                <entry>/etc/hosts.allow /etc/hosts.deny /etc/nologin
                                    /etc/ssh/sshd_config /etc/ssh_known_hosts /etc/sshrc sshd ssh-keygen</entry>
                            </row>
                        </tbody>
                    </tgroup>
                </table>
                <bridgehead>Topic 114: Security</bridgehead>
                <table pgwide="0">
                    <title>LPI Exam 102: Security</title>
                    <tgroup align="left" cols="4" colsep="1" rowsep="1">
                        <colspec colname="Weight" colwidth="0.5*"/>
                        <colspec colname="Title" colwidth="1.7*"/>
                        <colspec colname="Description" colwidth="4*"/>
                        <colspec colname="Key Files, terms and utillities" colwidth="2.5*"/>
                        <tbody>
                            <row>
                                <entry>Weight</entry>
                                <entry>Title</entry>
                                <entry>Description</entry>
                                <entry>Key Files, terms and utillities</entry>
                            </row>
                            <row>
                                <entry>3</entry>
                                <entry>Setup host security</entry>
                                <entry>Candidate should know how to set up a basic level of host
                                    security. Tasks include syslog configuration, shadowed
                                    passwords, set up of a mail alias for root's mail and turning of
                                    all network services not in use.</entry>
                                <entry>/etc/inetd.conf or /etc/inet.d/* /etc/nologin /etc/passwd
                                    /etc/shadow /etc/syslog.conf</entry>
                            </row>
                            <row>
                                <entry>4</entry>
                                <entry>Perform security administration tasks</entry>
                                <entry>Candidates should know how to review system configuration to
                                    ensure host security in accordance with local security policies.
                                    This objective includes how to configure TCP wrappers, find
                                    files with SUID/SGID bit set, verify packages, set or change
                                    user passwords and password aging information, update binaries
                                    as recommended by CERT, BUGTRAQ, and/or distribution's security
                                    alerts. Includes basic knowledge of ipchains and iptables.</entry>
                                <entry>/proc/net/ip_fwchains /proc/net/ip_fwnames
                                    /proc/net/ip_masquerade find ipchains passwd socket iptables</entry>
                            </row>
                            <row>
                                <entry>1</entry>
                                <entry>Setup user level security</entry>
                                <entry>Candidate should be able to configure user level security.
                                    Tasks include limits on user logins, processes, and memory
                                    usage. Key files, terms, and utilities include:</entry>
                                <entry>quota usermod</entry>
                            </row>
                        </tbody>
                    </tgroup>
                </table>
            </sect3>
        </sect2>
        <sect2>
            <title>Intermediate Level Administration (LPIC2)</title>
            <para>Status: Available now; published November 29, 2001 Pre-Requisites: Completion of
                LPIC Level 1 Requirements: Passing Exams 201 and 202 # Overview of Tasks: To pass
                Level 2 someone should be able to</para>
            <itemizedlist>
                <listitem>
                    <para>Administer a small to medium-sized site</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>Plan, implement, maintain, keep consistent, secure, and troubleshoot a
                        small mixed (MS, Linux) network, including a:</para>
                    <itemizedlist>
                        <listitem>
                            <para>LAN server (samba)</para>
                        </listitem>
                        <listitem>
                            <para>Internet Gateway (firewall, proxy, mail, news)</para>
                        </listitem>
                        <listitem>
                            <para>InternetServer(webserver,FTPserver)</para>
                        </listitem>
                    </itemizedlist>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>Supervise assistants</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>Advise management on automation and purchases</para>
                </listitem>
            </itemizedlist>
            <sect3>
                <title>LPI Exam 201</title>
                <bridgehead>Topic 201: Linux Kernel</bridgehead>
                <table pgwide="0">
                    <title>LPI Exam 201: The Linux Kernel</title>
                    <tgroup align="left" cols="4" colsep="1" rowsep="1">
                        <colspec colname="Weight" colwidth="0.5*"/>
                        <colspec colname="Title" colwidth="1.7*"/>
                        <colspec colname="Description" colwidth="4*"/>
                        <colspec colname="Key Files, terms and utillities" colwidth="2.5*"/>
                        <tbody>
                            <row>
                                <entry>Weight</entry>
                                <entry>Title</entry>
                                <entry>Description</entry>
                                <entry>Key Files, terms and utillities</entry>
                            </row>
                            <row>
                                <entry>1</entry>
                                <entry>Kernel Components</entry>
                                <entry>Candidates should be able to utilize kernel components that
                                    are necessary to specific hardware, hardware drivers, system
                                    resources and requirements. This objective includes implementing
                                    different types of kernel images, identifying stable and
                                    development kernels and patches, as well as using kernel modules.</entry>
                                <entry>zImage bzImage</entry>
                            </row>
                            <row>
                                <entry>1</entry>
                                <entry>Compiling a kernel</entry>
                                <entry>Candidates should be able to properly compile a kernel to
                                    include or disable specific features of the Linux kernel as
                                    necessary. This objective includes compiling and recompiling the
                                    Linux kernel as needed, implementing updates and noting changes
                                    in a new kernel, creating a system initrd image, and installing
                                    new kernels.</entry>
                                <entry>/usr/src/Linux/ /etc/lilo.conf make options (config, xconfig,
                                    menuconfig, oldconfig, mrproper zImage, bzImage, modules,
                                    modules_install) mkinitrd (both Red Hat and Debian based) make</entry>
                            </row>
                            <row>
                                <entry>1</entry>
                                <entry>Customizing a kernel</entry>
                                <entry>Candidates should be able to customize a kernel for specific
                                    system requirements by patching, compiling, and editing
                                    configuration files as required. This objective includes being
                                    able to assess requirements for a kernel compile versus a kernel
                                    patch as well as build and configure kernel modules.</entry>
                                <entry>/usr/src/Linux /proc/sys/kernel/ /etc/conf.modules,
                                    /etc/modules.conf patch make modprobe insmod, lsmod kerneld kmod</entry>
                            </row>
                            <row>
                                <entry>2</entry>
                                <entry>Patching a kernel</entry>
                                <entry>Candidates should be able to properly patch a kernel for
                                    various purposes including to implement kernel updates, to
                                    implement bug fixes, and to add support for new hardware. This
                                    objective also includes being able to properly remove kernel
                                    patches from existing production kernels.</entry>
                                <entry>Makefile patch gzip bzip</entry>
                            </row>
                        </tbody>
                    </tgroup>
                </table>
                <bridgehead>Topic 202:</bridgehead>
                <table pgwide="0">
                    <title>LPI Exam 201: System Startup</title>
                    <tgroup align="left" cols="4" colsep="1" rowsep="1">
                        <colspec colname="Weight" colwidth="0.5*"/>
                        <colspec colname="Title" colwidth="1.7*"/>
                        <colspec colname="Description" colwidth="4*"/>
                        <colspec colname="Key Files, terms and utillities" colwidth="2.5*"/>
                        <tbody>
                            <row>
                                <entry>Weight</entry>
                                <entry>Title</entry>
                                <entry>Description</entry>
                                <entry>Key Files, terms and utillities</entry>
                            </row>
                            <row>
                                <entry>2</entry>
                                <entry>Customizing system startup and boot processes</entry>
                                <entry>Candidates should be able to edit appropriate system startup
                                    scripts to customize standard system run levels and boot
                                    processes. This objective includes interacting with run levels
                                    and creating custom initrd images as needed.</entry>
                                <entry>/etc/init.d/ /etc/inittab /etc/rc.d/ mkinitrd (both Red Hat
                                    and Debian scripts)</entry>
                            </row>
                            <row>
                                <entry>3</entry>
                                <entry>System recovery</entry>
                                <entry>Candidates should be able to properly manipulate a Linux
                                    system during both the boot process and during recovery mode.
                                    This objective includes using both the init utility and init=
                                    kernel options.</entry>
                                <entry>inittab LILO init mount fsck</entry>
                            </row>
                        </tbody>
                    </tgroup>
                </table>
                <bridgehead>Topic 203: Filesystem</bridgehead>
                <table pgwide="0">
                    <title>LPI Exam 201: Filesystem</title>
                    <tgroup align="left" cols="4" colsep="1" rowsep="1">
                        <colspec colname="Weight" colwidth="0.5*"/>
                        <colspec colname="Title" colwidth="1.7*"/>
                        <colspec colname="Description" colwidth="4*"/>
                        <colspec colname="Key Files, terms and utillities" colwidth="2.5*"/>
                        <tbody>
                            <row>
                                <entry>Weight</entry>
                                <entry>Title</entry>
                                <entry>Description</entry>
                                <entry>Key Files, terms and utillities</entry>
                            </row>
                            <row>
                                <entry>3</entry>
                                <entry>Operating</entry>
                                <entry>the Linux filesystem Candidates should be able to properly
                                    configure and navigate the standard Linux filesystem. This
                                    objective includes configuring and mounting various filesystem
                                    types. Also included, is manipulating filesystems to adjust for
                                    disk space requirements or device additions.</entry>
                                <entry>/etc/fstab /etc/mtab /proc/mounts mount and umount sync
                                    swapon swapoff</entry>
                            </row>
                            <row>
                                <entry>3</entry>
                                <entry>Creating and configuring filesystem options</entry>
                                <entry>Candidates should be able to configure automount filesystems.
                                    This objective includes configuring automount for network and
                                    device filesystems. Also included is creating non ext2
                                    filesystems for devices such as CD-ROMs.</entry>
                                <entry>/etc/auto.master /etc/auto.[dir] mkisofs dd mke2fs</entry>
                            </row>
                            <row>
                                <entry>4</entry>
                                <entry>Maintaining a Linux filesystem</entry>
                                <entry>Candidates should be able to properly maintain a Linux
                                    filesystem using system utilities. This objective includes
                                    manipulating a standard ext2 filesystem.</entry>
                                <entry>fsck (fsck.ext2) badblocks mke2fs dumpe2fs debuge2fs tune2fs</entry>
                            </row>
                        </tbody>
                    </tgroup>
                </table>
                <bridgehead>Topic 204: Hardware</bridgehead>
                <table pgwide="0">
                    <title>LPI Exam 201: Hardware</title>
                    <tgroup align="left" cols="4" colsep="1" rowsep="1">
                        <colspec colname="Weight" colwidth="0.5*"/>
                        <colspec colname="Title" colwidth="1.7*"/>
                        <colspec colname="Description" colwidth="4*"/>
                        <colspec colname="Key Files, terms and utillities" colwidth="2.5*"/>
                        <tbody>
                            <row>
                                <entry>Weight</entry>
                                <entry>Title</entry>
                                <entry>Description</entry>
                                <entry>Key Files, terms and utillities</entry>
                            </row>
                            <row>
                                <entry>1</entry>
                                <entry>Configuring PCMCIA devices</entry>
                                <entry>Candidates should be able to configure a Linux installation
                                    to include PCMCIA support. This objective includes configuring
                                    PCMCIA devices, such as ethernet adapters, to autodetect when inserted.</entry>
                                <entry>/etc/pcmcia/ *.opts cardctl cardmgr</entry>
                            </row>
                            <row>
                                <entry>2</entry>
                                <entry>Configuring RAID</entry>
                                <entry>Candidates should be able to configure and implement software
                                    RAID. This objective includes using mkraid tools and configuring
                                    RAID 0, 1, and 5.</entry>
                                <entry>/etc/raidtab mkraid</entry>
                            </row>
                            <row>
                                <entry>2</entry>
                                <entry>Software and kernel configuration</entry>
                                <entry>Candidates should be able to configure kernel options to
                                    support various hardware devices including UDMA66 drives and IDE
                                    CD burners. This objective includes using LVM (Logical Volume
                                    Manager) to manage hard disk drives and particitions as well as
                                    software tools to interact with hard disk settings.</entry>
                                <entry>/proc/interrupts hdparm tune2fs sysctl</entry>
                            </row>
                            <row>
                                <entry>3</entry>
                                <entry>Adding new hardware</entry>
                                <entry>Candidates should be able to configure internal and external
                                    devices for a system including new hard disks, dumb terminal
                                    devices, serial UPS devices, multi-port serial cards, and LCD panels.</entry>
                                <entry>/proc/bus/usb XFree86 modprobe lsmod lsdev lspci setserial usbview</entry>
                            </row>
                        </tbody>
                    </tgroup>
                </table>
                <bridgehead>Topic 209: File and Service Sharing</bridgehead>
                <table pgwide="0">
                    <title>LPI Exam 201: File and Service Sharing</title>
                    <tgroup align="left" cols="4" colsep="1" rowsep="1">
                        <colspec colname="Weight" colwidth="0.5*"/>
                        <colspec colname="Title" colwidth="1.7*"/>
                        <colspec colname="Description" colwidth="4*"/>
                        <colspec colname="Key Files, terms and utillities" colwidth="2.5*"/>
                        <tbody>
                            <row>
                                <entry>Weight</entry>
                                <entry>Title</entry>
                                <entry>Description</entry>
                                <entry>Key Files, terms and utillities</entry>
                            </row>
                            <row>
                                <entry>5</entry>
                                <entry>Configuring a samba server</entry>
                                <entry>The candidate should be able to set up a Samba server for
                                    various clients. This objective includes setting up a login
                                    script for Samba clients, and setting up an nmbd WINS server.
                                    Also included is to change the workgroup in which a server
                                    participates, define a shared directory in smb.conf, define a
                                    shared printer in smb.conf, use nmblookup to test WINS server
                                    functionality, and use the smbmount command to mount an SMB
                                    share on a Linux client.</entry>
                                <entry>smbd, nmbd smbstatus, smbtestparm, smbpasswd, nmblookup
                                    smb.conf, lmhosts</entry>
                            </row>
                            <row>
                                <entry>3</entry>
                                <entry>Configuring an NFS server</entry>
                                <entry>The candidate should be able to create an exports file and
                                    specify filesystems to be exported. This objective includes
                                    editing exports file entries to restrict access to certain
                                    hosts, subnets or netgroups. Also included is to specify mount
                                    options in the exports file, configure user ID mapping, mount an
                                    NFS filesystem on a client, using mount options to specify soft
                                    or hard and background retries, signal handling, locking, and
                                    block size. The candidate should also be able to configure
                                    tcpwrappers to further secure NFS.</entry>
                                <entry>/etc/exports exportfs showmount nfsstat</entry>
                            </row>
                        </tbody>
                    </tgroup>
                </table>
                <bridgehead>Topic 211: System Maintenance</bridgehead>
                <table pgwide="0">
                    <title>LPI Exam 201: System Maintenance</title>
                    <tgroup align="left" cols="4" colsep="1" rowsep="1">
                        <colspec colname="Weight" colwidth="0.5*"/>
                        <colspec colname="Title" colwidth="1.7*"/>
                        <colspec colname="Description" colwidth="4*"/>
                        <colspec colname="Key Files, terms and utillities" colwidth="2.5*"/>
                        <tbody>
                            <row>
                                <entry>Weight</entry>
                                <entry>Title</entry>
                                <entry>Description</entry>
                                <entry>Key Files, terms and utillities</entry>
                            </row>
                            <row>
                                <entry>1</entry>
                                <entry>System logging</entry>
                                <entry>The candidate should be able to configure syslogd to act as a
                                    central network log server. This objective also includes
                                    configuring syslogd to send log output to a central log server,
                                    logging remote connections, and using grep and other text utils
                                    to automate log analysis.</entry>
                                <entry>syslog.conf /etc/hosts sysklogd</entry>
                            </row>
                            <row>
                                <entry>1</entry>
                                <entry>Packaging software</entry>
                                <entry>The candidate should be able to build a package. This
                                    objective includes building (or rebuilding) both RPM and DEB
                                    packaged software.</entry>
                                <entry>/debian/rules SPEC file format rpm</entry>
                            </row>
                            <row>
                                <entry>2</entry>
                                <entry>Backup operations</entry>
                                <entry>The candidate should be able to create an offsite backup
                                    storage plan.</entry>
                                <entry>Not applicable</entry>
                            </row>
                        </tbody>
                    </tgroup>
                </table>
                <bridgehead>Topic 213: System Customization and Automation</bridgehead>
                <table pgwide="0">
                    <title>LPI Exam 201: System Customization and Automation</title>
                    <tgroup align="left" cols="4" colsep="1" rowsep="1">
                        <colspec colname="Weight" colwidth="0.5*"/>
                        <colspec colname="Title" colwidth="1.7*"/>
                        <colspec colname="Description" colwidth="4*"/>
                        <colspec colname="Key Files, terms and utillities" colwidth="2.5*"/>
                        <tbody>
                            <row>
                                <entry>Weight</entry>
                                <entry>Title</entry>
                                <entry>Description</entry>
                                <entry>Key Files, terms and utillities</entry>
                            </row>
                            <row>
                                <entry>3</entry>
                                <entry>Automating tasks using scripts</entry>
                                <entry>The candidate should be able to write simple Perl scripts
                                    that make use of modules where appropriate, use the Perl taint
                                    mode to secure data, and install Perl modules from CPAN. This
                                    objective includes using sed and awk in scripts, and using
                                    scripts to check for process execution and generate alerts by
                                    email or pager if a process dies. Candidates should be able to
                                    write and schedule automatic execution of scripts to parse logs
                                    for alerts and email them to administrators, synchronize files
                                    across machines using rsync, monitor files for changes and
                                    generate email alerts, and write a script that notifies
                                    administrators when specified users log in or out.</entry>
                                <entry>perl -MCPAN -e shell bash, awk, sed crontab at</entry>
                            </row>
                        </tbody>
                    </tgroup>
                </table>
                <bridgehead>Topic 214: Troubleshooting</bridgehead>
                <table pgwide="0">
                    <title>LPI Exam 201: Troubleshooting</title>
                    <tgroup align="left" cols="4" colsep="1" rowsep="1">
                        <colspec colname="Weight" colwidth="0.5*"/>
                        <colspec colname="Title" colwidth="1.7*"/>
                        <colspec colname="Description" colwidth="4*"/>
                        <colspec colname="Key Files, terms and utillities" colwidth="2.5*"/>
                        <tbody>
                            <row>
                                <entry>Weight</entry>
                                <entry>Title</entry>
                                <entry>Description</entry>
                                <entry>Key Files, terms and utillities</entry>
                            </row>
                            <row>
                                <entry>1</entry>
                                <entry>Creating recovery disks</entry>
                                <entry>Candidate should be able to: create both a standard bootdisk
                                    for system entrance, and a recovery disk for system repair.</entry>
                                <entry>/etc/fstab /etc/inittab Any standard editor Familiarity with
                                    the location and contents of the LDP Bootdisk-HOWTO
                                    /usr/sbin/rdev /bin/cat /bin/mount (includes -o loop switch)
                                    /sbin/lilo /bin/dd /sbin/mke2fs /usr/sbin/chroot</entry>
                            </row>
                            <row>
                                <entry>1</entry>
                                <entry>Identifying boot stages</entry>
                                <entry>Candidate should be able to: determine, from bootup text, the
                                    4 stages of boot sequence and distinguish between each.</entry>
                                <entry>boot loader start and hand off to kernel kernel loading
                                    hardware initializiation and setup daemon initialization and setup</entry>
                            </row>
                            <row>
                                <entry>1</entry>
                                <entry>Troubleshooting LILO</entry>
                                <entry>Candidate should be able to: determine specific stage
                                    failures and corrective techniques.</entry>
                                <entry>/boot/boot.b Know meaning of L, LI, LIL, LILO, and scrolling
                                    010101 errrors Know the different LILO install locations, MBR,
                                    /dev/fd0, or primary/extended partition. Know significance of
                                    /boot/boot.### files</entry>
                            </row>
                            <row>
                                <entry>1</entry>
                                <entry>General troubleshooting</entry>
                                <entry>A candidate should be able to recognize and identify boot
                                    loader and kernel specific stages and utilize kernel boot
                                    messages to diagnose kernel errors. This objective includes
                                    being able to identify and correct common hardware issues, and
                                    be able to determine if the problem is hardware or software.</entry>
                                <entry>/proc filesystem Various system and daemon log files in
                                    /var/log/ /, /boot, and /lib/modules screen output during bootup
                                    kernel syslog entries in system logs (if entry is able to be
                                    gained) location of system kernel and attending modules dmesg
                                    /sbin/lspci /usr/bin/lsdev /sbin/lsmod /sbin/modprobe
                                    /sbin/insmod /bin/uname strace strings ltrace lsof</entry>
                            </row>
                            <row>
                                <entry>1</entry>
                                <entry>Troubleshooting system resources</entry>
                                <entry>A candidate should be able to identify, diagnose and repair
                                    local system environment.</entry>
                                <entry>/etc/profile &#38;&#38; /etc/profile.d/ /etc/init.d/
                                    /etc/rc.* /etc/sysctl.conf /etc/bashrc /etc/ld.so.conf (or other
                                    appropriate global shell configuration files) Core system
                                    variables Any standard editor /bin/ln /bin/rm /sbin/ldconfig /sbin/sysctl</entry>
                            </row>
                            <row>
                                <entry>1</entry>
                                <entry>Troubleshooting environment configurations</entry>
                                <entry>A candidate should be able to identify common local system
                                    and user environment configuration issues and common repair techniques.</entry>
                                <entry>/etc/inittab /etc/rc.local /etc/rc.boot
                                    /var/spool/cron/crontabs/ /etc/`shell_name`.conf /etc/login.defs
                                    /etc/syslog.conf /etc/passwd /etc/shadow /etc/group /etc/profile
                                    /sbin/init /usr/sbin/cron /usr/bin/crontab</entry>
                            </row>
                        </tbody>
                    </tgroup>
                </table>
            </sect3>
            <sect3>
                <title>Exam 202</title>
                <bridgehead>Topic XXX: Networking</bridgehead>
                <table pgwide="0">
                    <title>Exam 202: Networking</title>
                    <tgroup align="left" cols="4" colsep="1" rowsep="1">
                        <colspec colname="Weight" colwidth="0.5*"/>
                        <colspec colname="Title" colwidth="1.7*"/>
                        <colspec colname="Description" colwidth="4*"/>
                        <colspec colname="Key Files, terms and utillities" colwidth="2.5*"/>
                        <tbody>
                            <row>
                                <entry>Weight</entry>
                                <entry>Title</entry>
                                <entry>Description</entry>
                                <entry>Key Files, terms and utillities</entry>
                            </row>
                            <row>
                                <entry>5</entry>
                                <entry>Basic networking configuration</entry>
                                <entry>Modified: 2001-August-24 Maintainer: Kara Pritchard Weight: 5
                                    Description: The candidate should be able to configure a network
                                    device to be able to connect to a local network and a wide-area
                                    network. This objective includes being able to communicate
                                    between various subnets within a single network, configure
                                    dialup access using mgetty, configure dialup access using a
                                    modem or ISDN, configure authentication protocols such as PAP
                                    and CHAP, and configure TCP/IP logging.</entry>
                                <entry>/sbin/route /sbin/ifconfig /sbin/arp /usr/sbin/arpwatch /etc/</entry>
                            </row>
                            <row>
                                <entry>3</entry>
                                <entry>Advanced Network Configuration and Troubleshooting</entry>
                                <entry>The candidate should be able to configure a network device to
                                    implement various network authentication schemes. This objective
                                    includes configuring a multi-homed network device, configuring a
                                    virtual private network and resolving networking and
                                    communication problems.</entry>
                                <entry>/sbin/route /sbin/route /sbin/ifconfig /bin/netstat /bin/ping
                                    /sbin/arp /usr/sbin/tcpdump /usr/sbin/lsof /usr/bin/nc</entry>
                            </row>
                        </tbody>
                    </tgroup>
                </table>
                <bridgehead>Topic 206: Mail &#38; News</bridgehead>
                <table pgwide="0">
                    <title>Exam 202: Mail &#38; news</title>
                    <tgroup align="left" cols="4" colsep="1" rowsep="1">
                        <colspec colname="Weight" colwidth="0.5*"/>
                        <colspec colname="Title" colwidth="1.7*"/>
                        <colspec colname="Description" colwidth="4*"/>
                        <colspec colname="Key Files, terms and utillities" colwidth="2.5*"/>
                        <tbody>
                            <row>
                                <entry>Weight</entry>
                                <entry>Title</entry>
                                <entry>Description</entry>
                                <entry>Key Files, terms and utillities</entry>
                            </row>
                            <row>
                                <entry>1</entry>
                                <entry>Serving news</entry>
                                <entry>Candidates should be able to install and configure news
                                    servers using inn. This objective includes customizing and
                                    monitoring served newsgroups.</entry>
                                <entry>innd</entry>
                            </row>
                            <row>
                                <entry>1</entry>
                                <entry>Configuring mailing lists</entry>
                                <entry>Install and maintain mailing lists using majordomo. Monitor
                                    majordomo problems by viewing majordomo logs.</entry>
                                <entry>Majordomo2</entry>
                            </row>
                            <row>
                                <entry>3</entry>
                                <entry>Managing Mail Traffic</entry>
                                <entry>Candidates shold be able to implement client mail management
                                    software to filter, sort, and monitor incoming user mail. This
                                    objective includes using software such as procmail on both
                                    server and client side.</entry>
                                <entry>procmail .procmailrc</entry>
                            </row>
                            <row>
                                <entry>Using Sendmail</entry>
                                <entry>4</entry>
                                <entry>Candidates should be able to manage a Sendmail configuration
                                    including email aliases, mail quotas, and virtual mail domains.
                                    This objective includes configuring internal mail relays and
                                    monitoring SMTP servers.</entry>
                                <entry>/etc/aliases sendmail.cw virtusertable genericstable</entry>
                            </row>
                        </tbody>
                    </tgroup>
                </table>
                <bridgehead>Topic 207 DNS</bridgehead>
                <table pgwide="0">
                    <title>Exam 202: DNS</title>
                    <tgroup align="left" cols="4" colsep="1" rowsep="1">
                        <colspec colname="Weight" colwidth="0.5*"/>
                        <colspec colname="Title" colwidth="1.7*"/>
                        <colspec colname="Description" colwidth="4*"/>
                        <colspec colname="Key Files, terms and utillities" colwidth="2.5*"/>
                        <tbody>
                            <row>
                                <entry>Weight</entry>
                                <entry>Title</entry>
                                <entry>Description</entry>
                                <entry>Key Files, terms and utillities</entry>
                            </row>
                            <row>
                                <entry>2</entry>
                                <entry>Basic BIND 8 configuration</entry>
                                <entry>The candidate should be able to configure BIND to function as
                                    a caching-only DNS server. This objective includes the ability
                                    to convert a BIND 4.9 named.boot file to the BIND 8.x named.conf
                                    format, and reload the DNS by using kill or ndc. This objective
                                    also includes configuring logging and options such as directoryh
                                    location for zone files.</entry>
                                <entry>/etc/named.conf /usr/sbin/ndc /usr/sbin/named-bootconf kill</entry>
                            </row>
                            <row>
                                <entry>3</entry>
                                <entry>Create and maintain DNS zones</entry>
                                <entry>The candidate should be able to create a zone file for a
                                    forward or reverse zone or root level server. This objective
                                    includes setting appropriate values for the SOA resource record,
                                    NS records, and MX records. Also included is adding hosts with A
                                    resource records and CNAME records as appropriate, adding hosts
                                    to reverse zones with PTR records, and adding the zone to the
                                    /etc/named.conf file using the zone statement with appropriate
                                    type, file and masters values. A candidate should also be able
                                    to delegate a zone to another DNS server.</entry>
                                <entry>contents of /var/named zone file Syntax resource record
                                    formats dig nslookup host</entry>
                            </row>
                            <row>
                                <entry>3</entry>
                                <entry>Securing a DNS server</entry>
                                <entry>The candidate should be able to configure BIND to run as a
                                    non-root user, and configure BIND to run in a chroot jail. This
                                    objective includes configuring DNSSEC statements such as key and
                                    trusted-keys to prevent domain spoofing. Also included is the
                                    ability to configure a split DNS configuration using the
                                    forwarders statement, and specifying a non-standard version
                                    number string in response to queries.</entry>
                                <entry>SysV init files or rc.local /etc/named.conf /etc/passwd dnskeygen</entry>
                            </row>
                        </tbody>
                    </tgroup>
                </table>
                <bridgehead>Topic 208 Web Services</bridgehead>
                <table pgwide="0">
                    <title>Exam 202: Web Services</title>
                    <tgroup align="left" cols="4" colsep="1" rowsep="1">
                        <colspec colname="Weight" colwidth="0.5*"/>
                        <colspec colname="Title" colwidth="1.7*"/>
                        <colspec colname="Description" colwidth="4*"/>
                        <colspec/>
                        <colspec colname="Key Files, terms and utillities" colwidth="2.5*"/>
                        <tbody>
                            <row>
                                <entry>Weight</entry>
                                <entry>Title</entry>
                                <entry>Description</entry>
                                <entry>Key Files, terms and utillities</entry>
                            </row>
                            <row>
                                <entry>2</entry>
                                <entry>Implementing a web server</entry>
                                <entry>Candidates should be able to install and configure an Apache
                                    web server. This objective includes monitoring Apache load and
                                    performance, restricting client user access, configuring
                                    mod_perl and PHP support, and setting up client user
                                    authentication. Also included is configuring Apache server
                                    options such as maximum requests, minimum and maximim servers,
                                    and clients.</entry>
                                <entry>access.log .htaccess httpd.conf mod_auth htpasswd htgroup</entry>
                            </row>
                            <row>
                                <entry>2</entry>
                                <entry>Maintaining a web server</entry>
                                <entry>Candidates should be able to configure Apache to use virtual
                                    hosts for websites without dedicated IP addresses. This
                                    objective also includes creating an SSL certification for Apache
                                    and defining SSL definitions in configuration files using
                                    OpenSSL. Also included is customizing file access by
                                    implementing redirect statements in Apache's configuration files.</entry>
                                <entry>httpd.conf</entry>
                            </row>
                            <row>
                                <entry>2</entry>
                                <entry>Implementing a proxy server</entry>
                                <entry>Candidates should be able to install and configure a proxy
                                    server using Squid. This objective includes impelementing access
                                    policies, setting up authentication, and utilizing memory usage.</entry>
                                <entry>squid.conf acl http_access</entry>
                            </row>
                        </tbody>
                    </tgroup>
                </table>
                <bridgehead>Topic 210 Network Client Management</bridgehead>
                <table pgwide="0">
                    <title>Exam 202: Network Client Management</title>
                    <tgroup align="left" cols="4" colsep="1" rowsep="1">
                        <colspec colname="Weight" colwidth="0.5*"/>
                        <colspec colname="Title" colwidth="1.7*"/>
                        <colspec colname="Description" colwidth="4*"/>
                        <colspec colname="Key Files, terms and utillities" colwidth="2.5*"/>
                        <tbody>
                            <row>
                                <entry>Weight</entry>
                                <entry>Title</entry>
                                <entry>Description</entry>
                                <entry>Key Files, terms and utillities</entry>
                            </row>
                            <row>
                                <entry>1</entry>
                                <entry>NIS configuration</entry>
                                <entry>The candidate should be able to configure an NIS server and
                                    create NIS maps for major configuration files. This objective
                                    includes configuring a system as a NIS client, setting up an NIS
                                    slave server, and configuring ability to search local files,
                                    DNS, NIS, etc. in nsswitch.conf.</entry>
                                <entry>nisupdate, ypbind, ypcat, ypmatch, ypserv, ypswitch,
                                    yppasswd, yppoll, yppush, ypwhich, rpcinfo nis.conf,
                                    nsswitch.conf, ypserv.conf Contents of /etc/nis/: netgroup,
                                    nicknames, securenets Makefile</entry>
                            </row>
                            <row>
                                <entry>1</entry>
                                <entry>LDAP configuration</entry>
                                <entry>The candidate should be able to configure an LDAP server.
                                    This objective includes configuring a directory hierarchy,
                                    adding group, hosts, services and other data to the hierarchy.
                                    Also included is importing items from LDIF files and add items
                                    with a management tool, as well as adding users to the directory
                                    and change their passwords.</entry>
                                <entry>slapd slapd.conf</entry>
                            </row>
                            <row>
                                <entry>2</entry>
                                <entry>DHCP configuration</entry>
                                <entry>The candidate should be able to configure a DHCP server and
                                    set default options, create a subnet, and create a
                                    dynamically-allocated range. This objective includes adding a
                                    static host, setting options for a single host, and adding bootp
                                    hosts. Also included is to configure a DHCP relay agent, and
                                    reload the DHCP server after making changes.</entry>
                                <entry>dhcpd.conf dhcpd.leases</entry>
                            </row>
                            <row>
                                <entry>2</entry>
                                <entry>PAM authentication</entry>
                                <entry>The candidate should be able to configure PAM to support
                                    authentication via traditional /etc/passwd, shadow passwords,
                                    NIS, or LDAP.</entry>
                                <entry>/etc/pam.d pam.conf</entry>
                            </row>
                        </tbody>
                    </tgroup>
                </table>
                <bridgehead>Topic 212 System Security</bridgehead>
                <table pgwide="0">
                    <title>Exam 202: System Security</title>
                    <tgroup align="left" cols="4" colsep="1" rowsep="1">
                        <colspec colname="Weight" colwidth="0.5*"/>
                        <colspec colname="Title" colwidth="1.7*"/>
                        <colspec colname="Description" colwidth="4*"/>
                        <colspec colname="Key Files, terms and utillities" colwidth="2.5*"/>
                        <tbody>
                            <row>
                                <entry>Weight</entry>
                                <entry>Title</entry>
                                <entry>Description</entry>
                                <entry>Key Files, terms and utillities</entry>
                            </row>
                            <row>
                                <entry>1</entry>
                                <entry>TCP_wrappers</entry>
                                <entry>The candidate should be able to configure tcpwrappers to
                                    allow connections to specified servers from only certain hosts
                                    or subnets.</entry>
                                <entry>inetd.conf, tcpd hosts.allow, hosts.deny xinetd</entry>
                            </row>
                            <row>
                                <entry>2</entry>
                                <entry>Securing FTP servers</entry>
                                <entry>The candidate should be able to configure an anonymous
                                    download FTP server. This objective includes configuring an FTP
                                    server to allow anonymous uploads, listing additional
                                    precautions to be taken if anonymous uploads are permitted,
                                    configuring guest users and groups with chroot jail, and
                                    configuring ftpaccess to deny access to named users or groups.</entry>
                                <entry>ftpaccess, ftpusers, ftpgroups /etc/passwd chroot</entry>
                            </row>
                            <row>
                                <entry>2</entry>
                                <entry>Configuring a router</entry>
                                <entry>The candidate should be able to configure ipchains and
                                    iptables to perform IP masquerading, and state the significance
                                    of Network Address Translation and Private Network Addresses in
                                    protecting a network. This objective includes configuring port
                                    redirection, listing filtering rules, and writing rules that
                                    accept or block datagrams based upon source or destination
                                    protocol, port and address. Also included is saving and
                                    reloading filtering configurations, using settings in
                                    /proc/sys/net/ipv4 to respond to DOS attacks, using
                                    /proc/sys/net/ipv4/ip_forward to turn IP forwarding on and off,
                                    and usingtools such as PortSentry to block port scans and
                                    vulnerability probes.</entry>
                                <entry>/proc/sys/net/ipv4 /etc/services ipchains iptables routed</entry>
                            </row>
                            <row>
                                <entry>2</entry>
                                <entry>Secure shell (OpenSSH)</entry>
                                <entry>The candidate should be able to configure sshd to allow or
                                    deny root logins, enable or disable X forwarding. This objective
                                    includes generating server keys, generating a user's
                                    public/private key pair, adding a public key to a user's
                                    authorized_keys file, and configuring ssh-agent for all users.
                                    Candidates should also be able to configure port forwarding to
                                    tunnel an application protocol over ssh, configure ssh to
                                    support the ssh protocol versions 1 and 2, disable non-root
                                    logins during system maintenance, configure trusted clients for
                                    ssh logins without a password, and make multiple connections
                                    from multiple hosts to guard against loss of connection to
                                    remote host following configuration changes.</entry>
                                <entry>ssh, sshd /etc/ssh/sshd_config ~/.ssh/identity.pub and
                                    identity, ~/.ssh/authorized_keys .shosts, .rhosts</entry>
                            </row>
                            <row>
                                <entry>3</entry>
                                <entry>Security tasks</entry>
                                <entry>The candidate should be able to install and configure
                                    kerberos and perform basic security auditing of source code.
                                    This objective includes arranging to receive security alerts
                                    from Bugtraq, CERT, CIAC or other sources, being able to test
                                    for open mail relays and anonymous FTP servers, installing and
                                    configuring an intrusion detection system such as snort or
                                    Tripwire. Candidates should also be able to update the IDS
                                    configuration as new vulnerabilities are discovered and apply
                                    security patches and bugfixes.</entry>
                                <entry>Tripwire telnet nmap</entry>
                            </row>
                        </tbody>
                    </tgroup>
                </table>
                <bridgehead>Topic 214 Network Troubleshooting</bridgehead>
                <table pgwide="0">
                    <title>Exam 202: Network Troubleshooting</title>
                    <tgroup align="left" cols="4" colsep="1" rowsep="1">
                        <colspec colname="Weight" colwidth="0.5*"/>
                        <colspec colname="Title" colwidth="1.7*"/>
                        <colspec colname="Description" colwidth="4*"/>
                        <colspec colname="Key Files, terms and utillities" colwidth="2.5*"/>
                        <tbody>
                            <row>
                                <entry>Weight</entry>
                                <entry>Title</entry>
                                <entry>Description</entry>
                                <entry>Key Files, terms and utillities</entry>
                            </row>
                            <row>
                                <entry>1</entry>
                                <entry>Troubleshooting network issues</entry>
                                <entry>A candidates should be able to identify and correct common
                                    network setup issues to include knowledge of locations for basic
                                    configuration files and commands.</entry>
                                <entry>/sbin/ifconfig /sbin/route /bin/netstat /etc/network ||
                                    /etc/sysconfig/network-scripts/ system log files such as
                                    /var/log/syslog &#38;&#38; /var/log/messages /bin/ping
                                    /etc/resolv.conf /etc/hosts /etc/hosts.allow &#38;&#38;
                                    /etc/hosts.deny /etc/hostname || /etc/HOSTNAME /sbin/hostname
                                    /usr/sbin/traceroute /usr/bin/nslookup /usr/bin/dig /bin/dmesg host</entry>
                            </row>
                        </tbody>
                    </tgroup>
                </table>
            </sect3>
        </sect2>
    </sect1>
</appendix>
