<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!--<!DOCTYPE book PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.3//EN"
                      "http://www.docbook.org/xml/4.3/docbookx.dtd" [
<!ENTITY % globalents SYSTEM "../global.ent">
%globalents;
]>-->
<chapter id="certification">
    <title>Linux Distributions and Certifications</title>
    <sect1 id="LicensinganddetailsforDebianRedHatandSuSE">
        <sect1info>
            <title>Licensing and availability details for Debian, Red Hat and SuSE</title>
        </sect1info>
        <title>Licensing and availability details for SUSE, Red Hat and Debian GNU/Linux</title>
        <para>There are literally hundreds of Linux Distributions available. Size-wise they extend
            from versions that fit onto one 3.5 inch disk to those that are a few gigabytes big.</para>
        <para>Although there are differences from one version of this operating system to another,
            they all use the Linux Kernel (albeit different versions of the kernel</para>
        <para>We will discuss three of the Linux distributions that are most widely used, namely:
            SuSE, Red Hat, and Debian</para>
        <sect2>
            <title>
                <trademark>SUSE Linux</trademark>
            </title>
            <para>Novell announced<footnote>
                    <para>
                        <ulink url="http://www.novell.com/news/press/archive/2003/11/pr03069.html">Novell.com</ulink>
                    </para>
                </footnote> on November the 4th 2003, that they have made an agreement to acquire
                    <trademark>SUSE Linux</trademark>
                <footnote>
                    <para>SUSE is a registered trademark of <trademark>SUSE Linux</trademark>
                    </para>
                </footnote>, this purchase is subject to regulatory approval, but is expected to be
                allowed and finalized by the first quarter of 2004.</para>
            <bridgehead>Home Users</bridgehead>
            <para>This is how <trademark>SUSE</trademark> describes SUSE Linux 9.0, which is the
                family of products aimed at the home user:<footnote>
                    <para>
                        <ulink url="http://www.suse.com/us/private/products/suse_Linux/"/>
                    </para>
                </footnote>
            </para>
            <para>
                <quote> Migrating from Windows has never been easier: SUSE Linux 9.0 is secure and
                    stable. In addition to a powerful operating system, SUSE Linux 9.0 delivers all
                    the applications you need for Internet, Office, Multimedia, and Home networking.
                    Its installation routine is now almost fully automated, so you'll be up and
                    running with little effort. And, of course, you are assured all the advantages
                    of using Open Source software. </quote>
            </para>
            <bridgehead>System Requirements for <trademark>SUSE Linux 9.0 </trademark>
            </bridgehead>
            <itemizedlist id="SysReqSuse9.0">
                <listitem>
                    <para>Processor</para>
                    <itemizedlist>
                        <listitem>
                            <para>Intel: Celeron, Pentium to Pentium 4, Xeon</para>
                        </listitem>
                        <listitem>
                            <para>AMD: K6/II/III, <trademark>Duron</trademark>,
                                <trademark>Athlon</trademark>, <trademark>Athlon</trademark> XP/MP,
                                    <trademark>Athlon 64</trademark>
                            </para>
                        </listitem>
                        <listitem>
                            <para>IBM</para>
                        </listitem>
                        <listitem>
                            <para>286, 386, 486 and Cyrix processors are not supported</para>
                        </listitem>
                    </itemizedlist>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>Main Memory</para>
                    <itemizedlist>
                        <listitem>
                            <para>At least 64 MB are required for the installation with YaST2 in
                                graphical mode; 128 MB recommended</para>
                        </listitem>
                    </itemizedlist>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>Hard disk</para>
                    <itemizedlist>
                        <listitem>
                            <para>400 MB to more than 3 GB (Personal Edition) or 6 GB (Professional
                                Edition) for the installation of all packages; 2 GB or more recommended</para>
                        </listitem>
                        <listitem>
                            <para>LBA48 hard disks are supported</para>
                        </listitem>
                    </itemizedlist>
                </listitem>
            </itemizedlist>
            <para>
                <trademark>SUSE Linux</trademark> 9.0 can be downloaded via FTP for free. You can
                choose to download the complete installation directory, a CD image, from which you
                can create a bootable CD that will download and install SUSE from the FTP server. It
                is not possible to create the installation CD's for <trademark>SUSE</trademark> from
                the directories on the FTP server. You can also download a demonstration version of
                <trademark>SUSE</trademark> that runs from a bootable CD<footnote>
                    <para>A list of FTP mirror sites can be found <ulink
                        url="http://www.suse.com/us/private/download/ftp/int_mirrors.html">here.</ulink>
                        From here you would be able to download the files you need to install
                            <trademark>SUSE Linux 9.0</trademark>
                    </para>
                </footnote>
            </para>
            <bridgehead>Enterprise Users</bridgehead>
            <para>
                <trademark>SUSE</trademark> currently has three products that businesses are
                suggested to use, these are <trademark>SUSE Linux Standard Sever 8</trademark>,
                    <trademark>SUSE Linux Enterprise Server 8</trademark> and <trademark>SUSE Linux
                    Openexchange Server 4.1</trademark>
            </para>
            <bridgehead>
                <trademark>SUSE Linux Standard Server 8</trademark>:</bridgehead>
            <para>This is how SUSE describes <trademark>SUSE Linux Standard Server 8</trademark>
            </para>
            <para>
                <quote> With its comprehensive graphical administration, SUSE Linux Standard Server
                    was designed for small organizations and departments that want to implement
                    their Internet access as well as e-mail, print, and file services in a reliable,
                    secure way. Standard Server is available for 32-bit processors (x86) from AMD
                    and Intel and supports up to two CPUs</quote>
                <footnote>
                    <para>From: <ulink url="http://www.suse.com/us/business/products/server/"/>
                    </para>
                </footnote>
            </para>
            <bridgehead>System Requirements for <trademark>SuSE Linux Standard Server 8</trademark>:</bridgehead>
            <itemizedlist id="SysReqSuSeStandServer8">
                <listitem>
                    <para>Reccomended CPU: 700 Mhz</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>Minmum RAM: 256 MB</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>Hard Disk Space Required for Installation: 1 GB</para>
                </listitem>
            </itemizedlist>
            <bridgehead>Features of <trademark>SuSE Linux Standard Server 8</trademark>:</bridgehead>
            <itemizedlist id="FeatSuseStandServ8">
                <listitem>
                    <para>File and print services for Linux and <trademark>Windows</trademark>
                    </para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>Primary Domain Controller (PDC) for <trademark>Windows</trademark>
                    </para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>Central user administration with directory service (LDAP)</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>E-mail server (IMAP) for all e-mail clients including:</para>
                    <itemizedlist>
                        <listitem>
                            <para>Definition of the mailbox quota</para>
                        </listitem>
                        <listitem>
                            <para>SPAM filter</para>
                        </listitem>
                        <listitem>
                            <para>Dial on demand</para>
                        </listitem>
                        <listitem>
                            <para>Fetching mail from other providers</para>
                        </listitem>
                    </itemizedlist>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>Internet gateway server including web cache, web content filter, and firewall</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>Automatic assignment of IP addresses via DHCP server</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>Administration of host names with Dynamic Name Service (DNS)</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>Secure access for clients, i.e. for external staff via Virtual Private
                        Network (VPN)</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>Application server</para>
                </listitem>
            </itemizedlist>
            <bridgehead>
                <trademark>SuSE Linux Enterprise Server 8</trademark>
            </bridgehead>
            <para>This is how SUSE describes <trademark>SUSE Linux Enterprise Server 8</trademark>
            </para>
            <para>
                <quote> SUSE Linux Enterprise Server 8 is a leading server operating system for
                    professional deployment in heterogeneous IT environment of all sizes and
                    sectors. It is available for all relevant hardware platforms, ranging from
                    AMD/Intel 32-bit and 64-bit processors to the entire IBM eServer series
                    including mainframes - one single server operating system with a uniform code basis!</quote>
                <footnote>
                    <para>From: <ulink url="http://www.suse.com/us/business/products/server/"/>
                    </para>
                </footnote>
            </para>
            <bridgehead>System Requirements for <trademark>SUSE Linux Enterprise Server 8</trademark>:</bridgehead>
            <itemizedlist id="SysReqSuseEnter8">
                <listitem>
                    <para>Recommended CPU: 800 MHz</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>Minimum RAM: 256 MB</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>Hard Disk Space required for installation: 1.2 GB</para>
                </listitem>
            </itemizedlist>
            <para>For a full list of <trademark>SuSE Linux Enterprise Server 8</trademark> Features,
                visit <ulink
                url="http://www.SuSE.com/en/business/products/server/sles/features.html">this</ulink> page</para>
            <para>A comparison of <trademark>SUSE Linux Standard Server 8</trademark> and
                    <trademark>SUSE Linux Enterprise Server 8</trademark> can be found <ulink url="http://www.suse.com/en/business/products/server/which_version/index.html">here.</ulink>
            </para>
            <bridgehead>
                <trademark>SUSE Linux Openexchange Server 4.1</trademark>
            </bridgehead>
            <para>This is how SUSE describes <trademark>SUSE Linux Openexchange Server 4.1</trademark>
            </para>
            <para>
                <quote> SUSE Linux Openexchange Server 4.1 is the trend-setting groupware and
                    communication solution that helps your company to progress - with superior
                    technical features, far-reaching hardware independence, smooth migration, and a
                    wide range of supported clients including Outlook clients from Outlook 98 and
                    various web browsers.For All Requirements</quote>
            </para>
            <para>
                <quote>On the basis of standardized protocols and Open Source components, SUSE Linux
                    Openexchange Server offers everything modern enterprises and organizations need
                    for communication: e-mail server, web server, groupware, collaboration, and messaging.</quote>
                <footnote>
                    <para>From:<ulink url="http://www.suse.com/us/business/products/openexchange/"/>
                    </para>
                </footnote>
            </para>
            <bridgehead>System Requirements for <trademark>SUSE Linux Openexchange Server 4.1</trademark>
            </bridgehead>
            <itemizedlist>
                <listitem>
                    <para>CPU(s): AMD <trademark>Athlon</trademark> /<trademark>Duron</trademark>,
                        Intel Pentium III/4 or compatible AMD K6 is not supported!</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>RAM: 256 MB</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>Hard disk space: 9 GB</para>
                </listitem>
            </itemizedlist>
            <!-- SUSE ends here -->
        </sect2>
        <!-- RED HAT Starts Here -->
        <sect2>
            <title>Red Hat</title>
            <para>Red Hat Linux is probably the most well known Linux distribution. The first
                version of Red hat was released in October 1994.</para>
            <para>Its success can be attributed to the commitment to support and the development of
                the RHCE certification. For this reason, many of the corporate companies choosing to
                use Open Source Software have selected Red Hat Products. They knew that with Red Hat
                they would be able to have reliable updates to the products and that there was a
                pool of trained Red Hat Support Engineers.</para>
            <!-- Fedora starts here -->
            <sect3>
                <title>Red Hat for Home Users: Fedora</title>
                <para>Late in 2003 Red Hat announced that they would stop supporting Red hat Linux 9
                    and instead release two new product lines, aimed at very different markets.</para>
                <para>Up until that time Red Hat Linux 9 and the earlier versions, were used in the
                    corporate environment and by home users.</para>
                <para>The version now meant for home users is called &quot;the Fedora Project&quot;</para>
                <para>This is how Red Hat describes the Fedora Project: &quot;The Fedora Project
                    is a Red-Hat-sponsored and community-supported open source project. It is also a
                    proving ground for new technology that may eventually make its way into Red Hat
                    products. It is not a supported product of Red Hat, Inc.&quot; <footnote>
                        <para>From:<ulink url="http://fedora.redhat.com/">http://fedora.redhat.com/</ulink>
                        </para>
                    </footnote>
                </para>
                <para>A more open development process is used for Fedora, than is for Red Hat
                    Enterprise Linux. The Red Hat Developers are still taking part in the
                    development of Fedora but more community driven development is encouraged.</para>
                <sect4>
                    <title>Fedora License</title>
                    <para>In my understanding, a user may make and distribute unmodified copies of
                        Fedora's source code and binary code. If the product is modified you may
                        only redistribute these files if all images that contain the Fedora
                        trademark is changed.</para>
                    <para>Fedora's binary and source files may be downloaded, for free, via FTP.</para>
                    <para>Please see <ulink url="http://fedora.redhat.com/download/">this</ulink>
                        page, for exact instructions on how to download Fedora's installation files.</para>
                    <sect5>
                        <title>Fedora System Requirements</title>
                        <itemizedlist>
                            <listitem>
                                <para>CPU: Note: The following CPU specifications are stated in
                                    terms of Intel processors. Other processors (notably, offerings
                                    from AMD, Cyrix, and VIA) that are compatible with and
                                    equivalent to the following Intel processors may also be used
                                    with Fedora Core.</para>
                                <itemizedlist>
                                    <listitem>
                                        <para>Pentium-class Note: Fedora Core 1 is optimised for
                                            Pentium PRO (and later) CPUs, but also supports
                                            Pentium-class CPUs. This approach has been taken because
                                            Pentium-class optimisations actually result in reduced
                                            performance for non-Pentium-class processors.</para>
                                    </listitem>
                                    <listitem>
                                        <para>Recommended for text-mode: 200 MHz Pentium-class or better</para>
                                    </listitem>
                                    <listitem>
                                        <para>Recommended for graphical: 400 MHz Pentium II or better</para>
                                    </listitem>
                                </itemizedlist>
                            </listitem>
                            <listitem>
                                <para>Hard Disk Space (NOTE: Additional space will be required for
                                    user data):</para>
                                <itemizedlist>
                                    <listitem>
                                        <para>Custom Installation (Minimal): 520MB</para>
                                    </listitem>
                                    <listitem>
                                        <para>Server: 870MB</para>
                                    </listitem>
                                    <listitem>
                                        <para>Personal Desktop: 1.9GB</para>
                                    </listitem>
                                    <listitem>
                                        <para>Workstation: 2.4GB</para>
                                    </listitem>
                                    <listitem>
                                        <para>Custom Installation (Everything): 5.3GB</para>
                                    </listitem>
                                </itemizedlist>
                            </listitem>
                            <listitem>
                                <para>Memory:</para>
                                <itemizedlist>
                                    <listitem>
                                        <para>Minimum for text-mode: 64MB</para>
                                    </listitem>
                                    <listitem>
                                        <para>Minimum for graphical: 192MB</para>
                                    </listitem>
                                    <listitem>
                                        <para>Recommended for graphical: 256MB</para>
                                    </listitem>
                                </itemizedlist>
                            </listitem>
                        </itemizedlist>
                    </sect5>
                </sect4>
                <!-- Fedora ends here -->
            </sect3>
            <!-- Red Hat Enterprise Products Start here -->
            <sect3>
                <title>Red Hat Enterprise Linux</title>
                <para>Red Hat has four products that are aimed for use in the corporate environment:</para>
                <sect4 id="RedHatEnterpriseLinuxWS">
                    <title>Red Hat Enterprise Linux ws</title>
                    <para>Designed for desktop/client systems, therefore it does not include the
                        server applications found in the Red Hat Enterprise Linux ES or AS. (see below).</para>
                    <sect5 id="RedHatEnterpWSCapSysReqSection">
                        <title>Red Hat Enterprise Linux ws capabilities and System Requirements</title>
                        <para>A Test Paragraph to see if it fixes the issue</para>
                        <itemizedlist id="RedHatEnterpWSCapSysReq">
                            <listitem>
                                <para>Capabilities:</para>
                                <itemizedlist>
                                    <listitem>
                                        <para>Mail</para>
                                    </listitem>
                                    <listitem>
                                        <para>Document Processing</para>
                                    </listitem>
                                    <listitem>
                                        <para>Browsing</para>
                                    </listitem>
                                    <listitem>
                                        <para>Instant Messaging</para>
                                    </listitem>
                                </itemizedlist>
                            </listitem>
                            <listitem>
                                <para>Supported hardware:</para>
                                <itemizedlist>
                                    <listitem>
                                        <para>Intel X86</para>
                                    </listitem>
                                    <listitem>
                                        <para>Intel Itanium</para>
                                    </listitem>
                                    <listitem>
                                        <para>AMD</para>
                                    </listitem>
                                    <listitem>
                                        <para>AMD64</para>
                                    </listitem>
                                </itemizedlist>
                            </listitem>
                        </itemizedlist>
                    </sect5>
                </sect4>
                <sect4 id="RedHatEnterpriseLinuxES">
                    <title>Red Hat Enterprise Linux ES</title>
                    <para>Designed for small/midrange servers. Has the same capabilities as Red Hat
                        Enterprise Linux AS, but its hardware support is less extensive. It supports
                        x-86 based systems, with up to 2 CPU's and 8 GB of memory.</para>
                    <para>It is ideally suited for network, file, print, mail, Web, and custom or
                        packaged business applications.</para>
                    <itemizedlist id="RedHatEnterpriseLinuxESSysReqCap">
                        <listitem>
                            <para>Capabilities:</para>
                            <itemizedlist>
                                <listitem>
                                    <para>Mail</para>
                                </listitem>
                                <listitem>
                                    <para>File (SMB/NFS)</para>
                                </listitem>
                                <listitem>
                                    <para>Print</para>
                                </listitem>
                                <listitem>
                                    <para>Accelerated Web (tux)</para>
                                </listitem>
                                <listitem>
                                    <para>Advanced Firewall (arptables)</para>
                                </listitem>
                                <listitem>
                                    <para>Extended Remote Shell Access/Mgmt</para>
                                </listitem>
                                <listitem>
                                    <para>DHCP</para>
                                </listitem>
                                <listitem>
                                    <para>DNS Nameserver</para>
                                </listitem>
                                <listitem>
                                    <para>Network Authentication (Kerberos)</para>
                                </listitem>
                                <listitem>
                                    <para>News</para>
                                </listitem>
                                <listitem>
                                    <para>Backup</para>
                                </listitem>
                                <listitem>
                                    <para>Dump Server (Netdump)</para>
                                </listitem>
                                <listitem>
                                    <para>Directory Server (LDAP)</para>
                                </listitem>
                                <listitem>
                                    <para>Remote Boot/Image Server</para>
                                </listitem>
                                <listitem>
                                    <para>SSL</para>
                                </listitem>
                            </itemizedlist>
                        </listitem>
                        <listitem>
                            <para>Supported Hardware:</para>
                            <itemizedlist>
                                <listitem>
                                    <para>x86 architectures, up to 2 CPU's</para>
                                </listitem>
                            </itemizedlist>
                        </listitem>
                    </itemizedlist>
                </sect4>
                <sect4 id="RedHatEnterpriseLinuxAS">
                    <title>Red Hat Enterprise Linux AS</title>
                    <para>Designed for high-end and mission-critical systems. This is Red Hat's top
                        of the range distribution and is certified on systems provided by Dell, HP,
                        IBM, and Sun. <footnote>
                            <para>See <ulink
                                url="http://www.redhat.com/software/rhel/as/">this</ulink> page for
                                full specifications for Red Hat enterprise Linux AS</para>
                        </footnote>
                    </para>
                    <para>It supports the largest commodity-architecture servers with up to 16 CPUs
                        and 64GB of main memory and is available with the highest levels of support.</para>
                    <sect5 id="RedHatEnterpriseLinuxASCapSysReq">
                        <title>Red Hat Enterprise Linux AS Capabilities and Supported Hardware</title>
                        <itemizedlist>
                            <listitem>
                                <para>Capabilities:</para>
                                <itemizedlist>
                                    <listitem>
                                        <para>Mail</para>
                                    </listitem>
                                    <listitem>
                                        <para>File (SMB/NFS)</para>
                                    </listitem>
                                    <listitem>
                                        <para>Print</para>
                                    </listitem>
                                    <listitem>
                                        <para>Accelerated Web (tux)</para>
                                    </listitem>
                                    <listitem>
                                        <para>Advanced Firewall (arptables)</para>
                                    </listitem>
                                    <listitem>
                                        <para>Extended Remote Shell Access/Mgmt</para>
                                    </listitem>
                                    <listitem>
                                        <para>DHCP</para>
                                    </listitem>
                                    <listitem>
                                        <para>DNS Nameserver</para>
                                    </listitem>
                                    <listitem>
                                        <para>Network Authentication (Kerberos)</para>
                                    </listitem>
                                    <listitem>
                                        <para>News</para>
                                    </listitem>
                                    <listitem>
                                        <para>Backup</para>
                                    </listitem>
                                    <listitem>
                                        <para>Dump Server (Netdump)</para>
                                    </listitem>
                                    <listitem>
                                        <para>Directory Server (LDAP)</para>
                                    </listitem>
                                    <listitem>
                                        <para>Remote Boot/Image Server</para>
                                    </listitem>
                                    <listitem>
                                        <para>SSL</para>
                                    </listitem>
                                </itemizedlist>
                            </listitem>
                            <listitem>
                                <para>Supported Hardware:</para>
                                <itemizedlist>
                                    <listitem>
                                        <para>Intel X86</para>
                                    </listitem>
                                    <listitem>
                                        <para>Intel Itanium</para>
                                    </listitem>
                                    <listitem>
                                        <para>AMD AMD64</para>
                                    </listitem>
                                    <listitem>
                                        <para>IBM zSeries</para>
                                    </listitem>
                                    <listitem>
                                        <para>IBM iSeries</para>
                                    </listitem>
                                    <listitem>
                                        <para>IBM pSeries</para>
                                    </listitem>
                                    <listitem>
                                        <para>IBM S/390</para>
                                    </listitem>
                                </itemizedlist>
                            </listitem>
                        </itemizedlist>
                    </sect5>
                </sect4>
                <sect4 id="RedHatProfessionalWorkstation">
                    <title>Red Hat Professional Workstation</title>
                    <para>Enterprise Linux for use in the home. Supports up x86 hardware, with up to
                        2 CPU's. Meaning that other than Fedora, this distribution does have
                        official support from Red Hat, this includes technical support as well as
                        security updates.</para>
                    <sect5 id="RedHatProWSCapHardW">
                        <title>Red Hat Professional Workstation capabilities and Supported Hardware</title>
                        <itemizedlist>
                            <listitem>
                                <para>Capabilities:</para>
                                <itemizedlist>
                                    <listitem>
                                        <para>Bluecurve, Ximian Evolution, OpenOffice.org, Mozilla</para>
                                    </listitem>
                                    <listitem>
                                        <para>Samba, NFS, CUPS</para>
                                    </listitem>
                                    <listitem>
                                        <para>GCC3.2</para>
                                    </listitem>
                                </itemizedlist>
                            </listitem>
                            <listitem>
                                <para>Supported Hardware:</para>
                                <itemizedlist>
                                    <listitem>
                                        <para>x86 architectures</para>
                                    </listitem>
                                </itemizedlist>
                            </listitem>
                        </itemizedlist>
                    </sect5>
                </sect4>
                <sect4 id="RedHatEnterpLicensing">
                    <title>Red Hat Enterprise Family Licensing</title>
                    <para>As with the Fedora Project, you are allowed to make and distribute
                        unmodified copies of the binary and source code. If you want to distribute
                        modified copies of the software or source code, you need to modify those
                        files which contain the trademark images of Red Hat.</para>
                    <para>The licenses may vary depending on the country and product, to view the
                        specific license for the product you are interested in, visit <ulink
                        url="http://www.redhat.com/licenses/">this</ulink> page.</para>
                </sect4>
                <!-- Red Hat Enterprise ends here -->
            </sect3>
            <!-- Red Hat Ends here -->
        </sect2>
        <!-- Debian Starts Here -->
        <sect2 id="Debian">
            <title>Debian GNU/Linux</title>
            <para>Debian GNU/Linux (to use the correct term, Debian used for short) is a completely
                free operating system, by this I mean that it contains no software that is released
                under a proprietary license. Some other Linux distributions contain code that is not
                free software. It currently uses the Linux kernel, but there are plans to use the
                GNU kernel in future releases. The latest stable release is 3.0r.1</para>
            <para>Debian can be downloaded via FTP or HTTP from <ulink
                url="http://www.debian.org/distrib/cd">this</ulink> page</para>
            <para>Or purchased from vendors, see <ulink
                url="http://www.debian.org/CD/vendors/">this</ulink> page</para>
            <para>There are three versions of Debian that are available: stable, testing and
                unstable. This describes the amount of development that has been done on the
                particular version, and what environment it is suited to. You would not want to run
                your company's servers with the unstable version of Debian!</para>
            <itemizedlist>
                <listitem>
                    <para>Stable: current version is 3.0r.2, codenamed 'Woody'.</para>
                    <itemizedlist>
                        <listitem>
                            <para>Debian suggests that end users use this version, Debian's security
                                team supports it. Released in July 2002. Latest update to this
                                version done on November 21st, 2003</para>
                        </listitem>
                    </itemizedlist>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>Testing: Current version is codenamed 'Sarge'.</para>
                    <itemizedlist>
                        <listitem>
                            <para>Contains packages (applications) that have not yet been released
                                in the Stable version, but which are planned to be released in the
                                Stable version in the future. It has more recent versions of the
                                software than Woody, but has no support from the Debian security team.</para>
                        </listitem>
                    </itemizedlist>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>Unstable: Codenamed 'Sid'.</para>
                    <itemizedlist>
                        <listitem>
                            <para>This version of Debian is the one where new packages are actively
                                being developed, generally this is only used by developers working
                                on the packages for Sid.</para>
                        </listitem>
                    </itemizedlist>
                </listitem>
            </itemizedlist>
            <itemizedlist>
                <listitem>
                    <para>Hardware Supported by Debian:</para>
                    <itemizedlist>
                        <listitem>
                            <para>Alpha ARM</para>
                        </listitem>
                        <listitem>
                            <para>HP PA-RISC</para>
                        </listitem>
                        <listitem>
                            <para>Intel x86</para>
                        </listitem>
                        <listitem>
                            <para>Intel IA-64</para>
                        </listitem>
                        <listitem>
                            <para>MIPS</para>
                        </listitem>
                        <listitem>
                            <para>Motorola 680x0</para>
                        </listitem>
                        <listitem>
                            <para>MIPS (DEC)</para>
                        </listitem>
                        <listitem>
                            <para>PowerPC</para>
                        </listitem>
                        <listitem>
                            <para>IBM S/390</para>
                        </listitem>
                        <listitem>
                            <para>SPARC</para>
                        </listitem>
                    </itemizedlist>
                </listitem>
            </itemizedlist>
            <para>Debian comes with more than 8700 packages, most of which are released under GPL
                licenses (or licenses that can be compared to the GPL). To view the list of packages
                that are available, visit <ulink
                url="http://www.debian.org/distrib/packages">this</ulink> page.</para>
            <para>The installation manuals for the different distributions and hardware
                architectures can be found on <ulink
                url="http://www.debian.org/releases/stable/installmanual">this</ulink> page. The
                respective system requirements are found in the installation manuals.</para>
            <para>When doing a minimal Debian installation, you need very little system resources.
                For example on the Intel x86 architecture you need 12 MB of memory and 250 MB hard
                drive space to install a console-based system. To install a system that includes the
                X Windows System, you need at least 400MB hard drive space.</para>
            <!-- Debian ends here -->
        </sect2>
    </sect1>
    <!-- Online Classmates Starts here. -->
    <sect1 id="OnLineClassmatesInformationandRegistration">
        <sect1info>
            <title>On Line Classmates Information and Registration</title>
        </sect1info>
        <title>On Line Classmates Information and Registration</title>
        <para>Apart from the normal HTML version of the manual, we also use Moodle, a Open Source
            Package . By using the moodle version of the manual, the student not only has access to
            the material but also would have easy access to fellow students who are also taking part
            in the courses. Some of the features of Moodle is its forums which are dedicated to
            specific parts of the course as well as the chat facilities. This allows the student to
            communicate more efficiently with fellow students as well as the maintainers and
            lecturers of the courses.</para>
        <para>Moodle was developed by Martin Dougiamas, visit <ulink url="http://www.moodle.org">www.moodle.org</ulink> for more information.</para>
        <para>The Moodle implementation of this manual can be found at <ulink url="http://learnlinux.tsf.org.za/moodle/">http://learnlinux.tsf.org.za/moodle/</ulink></para>
        <!--Online Classmates ends -->
    </sect1>
    <!-- Certification Starts -->
    <sect1 id="Certification">
        <title>Certification</title>
        <sect2 id="LPI">
            <title>Linux Professional Institute Certification</title>
            <para>The Linux Professional Institute currently has two levels of certification, Junior
                Level Administration (LPIC1) and Intermediate Level Administration (LPIC2). At the
                time of writing the Senior Level Administration (LPIC3) course was still being
                developed. </para>
            <para>With the permission of the LPI, we have created a detailed list of the skills you
                need to have to gain the different levels of certification. We have included this in
                the first appendix of this course <xref linkend="LPI_certification"/>
            </para>
        </sect2>
        <sect2 id="SairCertification">
            <!-- SAIR Linux and GNU Certification Starts -->
            <title>SAIR Linux and GNU Certification</title>
            <para>We intended to cover the SAIR Linux GNU certification as well, but it seems as if
                it no longer exists. From their home page <ulink
                url="http://www.Linuxcertification.org/">http://www.Linuxcertification.org/</ulink>
                it seems that this certification has been taken over by Thomson Learning corporate
                and professional training operations. We have made repeated attempts at contacting
                the new administrators of this certification, with no response. SAIR-GNU offered
                three levels of certification: Administrator (LCA), Engineer (LCE) and Master
                Engineer (MLCE).</para>
        </sect2>
        <!-- SAIR Linux and GNU Certification Ends -->
        <sect2 id="RedHatCertification">
            <!-- Red Hat Certification Starts -->
            <title>Red Hat Certification</title>
            <para>One of the reasons Red Hat has been so widely accepted in the Enterprise
                environment, I feel, is becasue it has created (and updated) its own certification
                for its products. People respect the RHCE certification, because it is not easy to
                attain. Unlike other certifications, the RHCE and RHCT exams are done on live test
                systems, that simulate tasks that System Administrators should be capable of doing.</para>
            <para>There are two levels of certification offered by Red Hat; RHCT (Red Hat Certified
                Technitian) and RHCE (Red Hat Certified Engineer). The RHCE is the more advanced
                certification. The RHCE and RHCT exams are performance based practical labs. In
                other words you are given a exam based on situations that you will find in the real
                world. As of the end of 2003 these exams are based on the Red Hat Enterprise family
                of products, not Red Hat 9 as it was previoulsy.</para>
            <sect3 id="RHCT">
                <!-- RHCT Starts -->
                <title>RHCT Certification</title>
                <para>According to Red Hat <footnote>
                        <para>
                            <ulink url="http://www.redhat.com/training/">http://www.redhat.com/training/</ulink>
                        </para>
                    </footnote>
                </para>
                <blockquote>
                    <para>RHCT tests a technician-specific subset of the skills tested in RHCE: *
                        RHCTs will typically not be making the decisions about how to set up
                        production network services and network security. Thus, RHCT does not test
                        the networking services and network security skills required to earn RHCE.</para>
                </blockquote>
                <para>The RHCT consists of the following exams:</para>
                <orderedlist>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>Troubleshooting and System Maintenance (1 hour)</para>
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>Installation and Configuration (2 hours)</para>
                    </listitem>
                </orderedlist>
                <important>
                    <para>To earn the RHCT certification one must successfully complete all the
                        requirements in Troubleshooting and System Maintenance and must attain at
                        least 70% for Installation and configuration.</para>
                    <para>Pre_requisite skills:</para>
                </important>
                <itemizedlist>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>use standard command line tools (e.g., ls, cp, mv, rm, tail, cat,
                            etc.) to create, remove, view, and investigate files and directories</para>
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>use grep, sed, and awk to process text streams and files</para>
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>use a terminal-based text editor, such as vi/vim, to modify text files</para>
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>use input/output redirection</para>
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>understand basic principles of TCP/IP networking, including IP
                            addresses, netmasks, and gateways</para>
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>use su to switch user accounts</para>
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>use passwd to set passwords</para>
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>use tar, gzip, and bzip2v</para>
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>configure an email client on Red Hat Enterprise Linux</para>
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>use mozilla and/or links to access HTTP/HTTPS URLs</para>
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>use lftp to access FTP URLs</para>
                    </listitem>
                </itemizedlist>
                <para>Skills needed for Troubleshooting and System Maintainenance exam:</para>
                <itemizedlist>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>boot systems into different run levels for troubleshooting and system maintenance</para>
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>diagnose and correct misconfigured networking</para>
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>diagnose and correct hostname resolution problems</para>
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>configure the X Window System and a desktop environment</para>
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>add new partitions, filesystems, and swap to existing systems</para>
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>use standard command-line tools to analyze problems and configure system</para>
                    </listitem>
                </itemizedlist>
                <para>Skills needed for Installation and Configuration Exam:</para>
                <itemizedlist>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>perform network OS installation</para>
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>implement a custom partitioning scheme</para>
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>configure printing</para>
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>configure the scheduling of tasks using cron and at</para>
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>attach system to a network directory service, such as NIS or LDAP</para>
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>configure autofs</para>
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>add and manage users, groups, and quotas</para>
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>configure filesystem permissions for collaboration</para>
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>install and update RPMs</para>
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>properly update the kernel RPM</para>
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>modify the system bootloader</para>
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>implement software RAID at install-time and run-time</para>
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>use /proc/sys and sysctl to modify and set kernel run-time parameters</para>
                    </listitem>
                </itemizedlist>
            </sect3>
            <!-- RHCTS ends -->
            <sect3 id="RHCE">
                <!-- The RHCE certification: Starts -->
                <title>The RHCE certification:</title>
                <para>The RHCE consists of the following exams:</para>
                <orderedlist>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>Troubleshooting (2.5 hours)</para>
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>Multiple Choice (1 hour)</para>
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>Installation and Configuration (2.5 hours)</para>
                    </listitem>
                </orderedlist>
                <important>
                    <para>To earn the RHCE one must successfully complete all the troubleshooting
                        tests, score a minimum of 50% for the multiple choice exam, score at least
                        70% for both the RHCE and RHCT components of the exams and attain a minimum
                        of at least 80% for the all the exams as a whole.</para>
                </important>
                <para>Pre_requisite skills:</para>
                <itemizedlist>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>use standard command line tools (e.g., ls, cp, mv, rm, tail, cat,
                            etc.) to create, remove, view, and investigate files and directories</para>
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>use grep, sed, and awk to process text streams and files</para>
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>use a terminal-based text editor, such as vi/vim, to modify text files</para>
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>use input/output redirection</para>
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>understand basic principles of TCP/IP networking, including IP
                            addresses, netmasks, and gateways</para>
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>use su to switch user accounts</para>
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>use passwd to set passwords</para>
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>use tar, gzip, and bzip2v</para>
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>configure an email client on Red Hat Enterprise Linux</para>
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>use mozilla and/or links to access HTTP/HTTPS URLs</para>
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>use lftp to access FTP URLs</para>
                    </listitem>
                </itemizedlist>
                <para>Skills needed for Troubleshooting and System Maintainenance exam:</para>
                <itemizedlist>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>boot systems into different run levels for troubleshooting and system maintenance</para>
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>diagnose and correct misconfigured networking</para>
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>diagnose and correct hostname resolution problems</para>
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>configure the X Window System and a desktop environment</para>
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>add new partitions, filesystems, and swap to existing systems</para>
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>use standard command-line tools to analyze problems and configure system</para>
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>use the rescue environment provided by first installation CD</para>
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>diagnose and correct bootloader failures arising from bootloader,
                            module, and filesystem errors</para>
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>diagnose and correct problems with network services (see Installation
                            and Configuration below for a list of these services)</para>
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>add, remove, and resize logical volumes</para>
                    </listitem>
                </itemizedlist>
                <para>Skills needed for Installation and Configuration Exam:</para>
                <itemizedlist>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>perform network OS installation</para>
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>implement a custom partitioning scheme</para>
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>configure printing</para>
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>configure the scheduling of tasks using cron and at</para>
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>attach system to a network directory service, such as NIS or LDAP</para>
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>configure autofs</para>
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>add and manage users, groups, and quotas</para>
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>configure filesystem permissions for collaboration</para>
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>install and update RPMs</para>
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>properly update the kernel RPM</para>
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>modify the system bootloader</para>
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>implement software RAID at install-time and run-time</para>
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>use /proc/sys and sysctl to modify and set kernel run-time parameters</para>
                    </listitem>
                </itemizedlist>
                <para>People wanting to attain the RHCE certification must be also capable of
                    configuring the following network services:</para>
                <itemizedlist>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>HTTP/HTTPS</para>
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>SMB</para>
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>NFS</para>
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>FTP</para>
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>Web proxy</para>
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>SMTP</para>
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>IMAP, IMAPS, and POP3</para>
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>SSH</para>
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>DNS</para>
                    </listitem>
                </itemizedlist>
                <para>For each of these services, RHCEs must be able to:</para>
                <itemizedlist>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>install the packages needed to provide the service</para>
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>configure the service to start when the system is booted</para>
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>configure the service for basic operation</para>
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>Configure host-based and user-based security for the service</para>
                    </listitem>
                </itemizedlist>
                <para>RHCEs must also be able to</para>
                <itemizedlist>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>configure hands-free installation using Kickstart</para>
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>implement logical volumes at install-time</para>
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>use PAM to implement user-level restrictions</para>
                    </listitem>
                </itemizedlist>
            </sect3>
            <!-- The RHCE certification: ENDS -->
        </sect2>
        <!-- Red Hat Certification Ends -->
        <!-- Certification ends -->
    </sect1>
</chapter>
