<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!--<!DOCTYPE book PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.3//EN"
                      "http://www.docbook.org/xml/4.3/docbookx.dtd" [
<!ENTITY % globalents SYSTEM "../global.ent">
%globalents;
]>-->
<chapter id="requirements">
    <title>Details of requirements for the courses</title>
    <sect1 id="MachineRequirements">
        <title>Machine Requirements</title>
        <para>You do not need a very poweful Computer to run Linux. If you did a console only
            installation (without a GUI windows environment) a Pentium 100 with 32 MB of memory and
            500 MB of hard drive space would be more than enough . Of course the more recent
            versions of Linux like <trademark>Red Hat</trademark> Enterprise 3 and <trademark>SUSE
            Linux</trademark> 9 would need a computer with more capabilities than a Pentium 1</para>
        <bridgehead>Fundamentals</bridgehead>
        <para>It is possible to run this course on Linux or in Windows - however when working in
            Windows you will have to install a Linux emulator. Matthew West created a Debian
            GNU/Linux image you can use with Bochs, an Open Source Emulator. We suggest you use this
            image and Bochs, since it also includes the sample files that Matthew West uses as
            examples and Exercises in the Fundamentlas course.</para>
        <para>What this does is to create a virtual enviroment, that runs inside your current
            Operating System, which runs Debian GNU/Linux. Download and installation instructions
            can be found <xref linkend="Emulator"/> here.</para>
        <para>Because this emulated (virtual) machine needs to use the resources of the installed
            Operating System you need a faster computer to run it successfully. We recommend a
            Pentium 2 500 Mhz computer with 32 MB memory. If you already have Linux installed you do
            not need to use the simulator.</para>
        <bridgehead>System Administration</bridgehead>
        <para>For the System Administration course you need only one machine. The System
            Administration course begins by explaining how to install Debian. Run this course after
            you have completed and are familiar with the material covered in the Fundamentals course.</para>
        <bridgehead>Networking</bridgehead>
        <para>For the Networking courses, you would need to have two machines with Linux installed
            on them. Both machines should have a Network card installed. If you are using a machine
            that is already connected to a Local Area Network then you do not need a second machine.</para>
        <bridgehead>Shell Scripting and Internals courses</bridgehead>
        <para>You need to have a Linux distribution installed to take part in these courses</para>
        <!-- Would the student need a Linux machine for the Internals course? -->
    </sect1>
    <sect1 id="CoursePreRequisitesandOutcomes">
        <sect1info>
            <title>Course Pre-requisites And Outcomes</title>
        </sect1info>
        <title>Course Pre-requisites And Outcomes</title>
        <sect2>
            <title>A theory that works</title>
            <para>In the technical world of computers today it is no longer really enough to just
                know or specialise in one area of technology. With the emphasis being on networking,
                you will need to know something of everything to really get by. (e.g. operating
                systems, routers and other networking equipment, system and network administration,
                system and network design, latest technology trends etcetera.)</para>
            <para>You will also need knowledge of the business structure in your company. Become a
                technical person able or capable of enhancing the business of the company or
                companies that you work for - almost operating as a business yourself
                (self-sustaining and self-enhancing).</para>
            <para>Some examples would be:</para>
            <itemizedlist>
                <listitem>
                    <para>Regular operating system maintenance will ensure good solid and consistent
                        performance - this could save the business a lot of money.</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>Another example would be that if you know the Open Source and Free
                        Software products available you could advise your company to go with that
                        solution rather than a propriety solution and this could go a long way to
                        ensuring that the business saves money.</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>Think laterally and carefully when supporting and Operating System like
                        Linux or Unix, being so powerful means that there is more to it than a
                        simple stream of instructions.</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>Become aware of what is happening around you in the computer industry and
                        in business and become a real asset.</para>
                </listitem>
            </itemizedlist>
            <para>A note aside:- <quote>Whilst working as a Unix technician, a new
                    &quot;client&quot; phoned me one day and asked me to install another
                    disk drive on the Unix server for them as their first hard drive was full. They
                    had been running this server for 4 years and I asked them to wait until I
                    arrived before purchasing another disk but I was too late they had ordered one
                    already. When I arrived I cleaned up the primary hard disk drive from 100% full
                    to 40% full just by doing thorough house-keeping (could have been handled with a
                    Shell Script running automatically each week/month), tidying up the log files,
                    temporary directories, superfluous software versions etcetera.</quote>
                <author>
                    <firstname>Simone</firstname>
                    <surname>Demblon</surname>
                </author>
            </para>
            <para>Once you have learnt one operating system in the way that we have structured this
                course, it is much easier to pick up other knowledge on hardware / operating
                systems, system configuration and even development.</para>
            <para>As it would be almost impossible to learn everything about all technology
                available, cultivate a technical way of thinking laterally, it will be a decided
                advantage to you.</para>
        </sect2>
        <sect2>
            <title>Pre-requisite knowledge and outcomes</title>
            <para>The text below is a mere guideline to equivalent knowledge, as you know if you
                have a talent for working with computers OR if you are an extremely hard-worker who
                is prepared to play with the operating system until you are sure of yourself, then
                you are likely to not need to follow these guidelines and you will exceed the
                qualification levels that are suggested here.</para>
            <para>Therefore when I say below that your knowledge would be equivalent to a System
                Administrator, what I am really saying is that although you will have an extensive
                knowledge of Linux (we have structured the courses to ensure that there are
                sufficient labs and Exercises), the additional knowledge - the knowledge of specific
                company set-ups or specific pieces of hardware - will still have to be gained by
                your experience.</para>
            <para>Now let's look at each course or course range and discuss the relevant issues:</para>
            <orderedlist numeration="arabic">
                <listitem>
                    <para>In order to successfully complete the Fundamentals course you will need to
                        have knowledge of PC Computers (operating systems and hardware).</para>
                    <para>After completion on the Fundamentals course (approximately 18 hours of
                        study), you would have a basic grounding of the Linux Operating System.</para>
                    <para>Please note however that although an introductory course to Linux it is
                        not an introduction to computers or operating systems. We assume that you
                        have some technical knowledge already.</para>
                    <para>In this course, some internal operations of the operating system are
                        covered simply, and this is in order to ensure that you are able to think a
                        problem through laterally. This will also assist if wishing to complete the
                        range all the way through to the Internals course, by giving you a grounding
                        in simple terms to build on throughout the other courses.</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>In order to successfully complete the System Administration course you
                        would need enough knowledge to install an operating system.</para>
                    <para>After completion of the Fundamentals and System Administration courses (18
                        + 30 hours), you would have the equivalent knowledge of a Junior
                        Administrator in Linux. You will have enough knowledge and experience
                        (through intensive labs) to assist a fully qualified System Administrator in
                        a commercial business situation. (RHCT)</para>
                    <para>At this stage all you will lack is further experience to enable you to
                        perform the function of System Administrator.</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>After further completing the Network Administrators course (30 hours), and
                        this would include all associated Exercises, labs and simulated problem
                        labs, you would be able to work as a Junior Network Administrator.</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>After completing the Elective course subjects, affiliated to the
                        Networking course, (18 hours) you would be qualified to do System and
                        Network Administration including monitoring and maintaining your network. (RHCE)</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>Shell Scripting (20 hours) is a course that will clarify the power of
                        Linux for you and will also excite you as pieces of the &quot;operating
                        system puzzle&quot; fall into pace at an alarming rate. This is a
                        stunning course and no matter what you intend to do with your Linux
                        knowledge this course is a must.Ensure that you have completed the following
                        courses or that you have equivalent knowledge prior to attempting this
                        course: Fundamentals, System Administration and Networking Introduction.</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>Internals^-1 is a technical course written to enable a System
                        Administrator to become a visionary systems engineer able to attend a full
                        internals course if so inclined. A cautionary note would be that although we
                        have kept it as generically inclined as possible you may have to check up
                        the variances with the Linux or Unix kernel that you are working with.</para>
                    <para>As we have said from the beginning, support of such an operating system is
                        going to take a fair amount of lateral thinking, and as not all of us are
                        interested in the nitty-gritty details of how an operating system was
                        written (see reference material used if you are interested), so internals^-1
                        will give you the workings in a more simple technical form. </para>
                </listitem>
            </orderedlist>
        </sect2>
    </sect1>
</chapter>
